<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer from the country to a late letter to a dissenter upon occassion of His Majesties late gracious declaration of indulgence by a member of the Church of England.</title>
            <author>Member of the Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 139 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25496</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3278</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16389</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13618179</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13618179</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100804</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25496)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100804)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 832:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer from the country to a late letter to a dissenter upon occassion of His Majesties late gracious declaration of indulgence by a member of the Church of England.</title>
                  <author>Member of the Church of England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for M.R.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 48.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Sovereign (1685-1688 : James II). --  His Majesties gracious declaration to all his loving subjects for liberty of conscience.</term>
               <term>Liberty of conscience --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Liberty of conscience --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100804:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER FROM THE COUNTRY, TO A LATE LETTER TO A DISSENTER, Upon Occaſion of His MAJESTIES Late GRACIOUS Declaration of Indulgence.</p>
            <p>By a Member of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>M. R.</hi> in the Year 1687:</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:100804:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100804:2"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER FROM THE COUNTRY, TO A Late <hi>Letter</hi> Writ to a <hi>Diſſenter,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is the unhappy ſtate of mankind, that the over-weening Opinions, and Sentiments, which by Education, or Cuſtom, we have entertain'd, incline, and warp our minds ſo to the maintaining of them; that we are as difficultly alter'd, as the Tree is, which bended, when a young ſappling, is rarely by any Art made ſtraight.</p>
            <p>Beſides this, the tempers of moſt Mens Souls are ſuch, that they eaſily divide into Parties, and being liſted, as in a ſtate of War, they ſtudy nothing more, than to convince, or ſubdue all thoſe who differ from them. Yea, we too frequently find, that they make thoſe the Object of their averſion or abhorrence, who ſtudy to compoſe their eager tempers, or direct them to any degree of humanity.</p>
            <p>Hence it is, that when National limits are not ſufficient cauſes of quarrels, the ranks and degrees of Men, the City and Country, Fraternities, Neighborhood, yea, Domeſtical Intereſts, crumble us, and caſt us into various figures.</p>
            <p>Theſe Jars, and Hoſtilities, are fomented by Intereſt, Ambition, and all the croſs-grain'd paſſions of our Souls; and when Religion mixes with our humane concerns, it ſublimes all their corroſive ſpirits, and is the univerſal diſſolvent.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:100804:3"/>
            <p>Every one is apt to think the fire of his own Altar the pureſt, and is not content to have liberty to trim his own Houſhold hearth, and warm himſelf at his own Faggot, but endeavours, according to his power, to make all gain-ſayers Victims and Sacrifices to his Deity; and when no Secular Intereſt moves them, the pretended eager Charity to ſave their Souls, and the preventing, as they call it, the ſpreading of that Infection, makes them mortify them in their Eſtates, or ſend them to the <hi>Peſt-houſe,</hi> or cut them off as gangren'd Members</p>
            <p>Hence it is, that the <hi>Roman Catholick Church,</hi> the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and Diſſenters, according as they have had the favour of the Government, or could exerciſe any Authority, have each of them puniſhed, or ſuppreſt the other, and have been more or leſs ſevere, according as the Government (judging it to conduce to ſecure the publick peace,) was inclin'd to embrace that Religion, or the deſires of Church-men were more or leſs preſſing, to bring all to Uniformity in Faith and Diſcipline.</p>
            <p>Former Ages have experimented this way of proceeding, and it hath been accompanied with the lowd cries of the ſuffering Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the decay of Trade, the unpeopling of Countries, and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine Seditions and Rebellions. Our unhappy Iſland hath not wanted Inſtances of the ill effects of arming by <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> Church Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities, one againſt the other; ſo that the Governing Parties, under Religious Denomination, have produced almoſt as much miſchief, as, in Ancient times, the Wars betwixt the Houſes of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter</hi> occaſioned; and however oppreſſive the State-Church of <hi>England</hi> is reputed, yet I think it will not be diſown'd, that when thoſe called <hi>Diſſenters</hi> got the Power in their hands, they made greater Ravage and Depredations in Twenty years, upon the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> and the Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> than had been inflicted on themſelves in an Age; witneſs the ſequeſtring, decimating, and ſeizing their Eſtates, Fining, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoning, Baniſhing, and putting to Death of ſo many, and ſelling the Lands of the Biſhops, Deans, and Chapters.</p>
            <p>Our Gracious King, revolving therefore in His Princely Mind the Fatalities that have attended this Conduct, and the unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and miſchievous Reſults of ſuch proceedings, (the effects whereof he had felt Himſelf,) hath, in His profound Wiſdom, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to try the moſt probable expedient, to ſtill and quiet theſe ſo long continued Animoſities, Contrarieties, and Ferments of His Subjects.</p>
            <p>Some publick notices of this He gave in the very beginning of His Reign, by Prohibiting in His Courts, and diſcountenancing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100804:3"/>upon the <hi>Penal Laws.</hi> But that I may diſcover the true ſteps the King made towards it, and the foot upon which the late <hi>Indulgence</hi> ſtands, and prevent ſome Repetitions, I ſhould o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe be neceſſiated to uſe in my Reply to your Letter; I ſhall ſuccinctly touch the Kings Progreſs, and the deportment of ſome Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and Diſſenters, before, and ſince the <hi>Indulgence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the Firſt Council the King held after his coming to the Crown, he expreſſed the ſenſe he had of the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> Loyalty, and gave us Aſſurances of His <hi>Defence</hi> and <hi>Support</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>This pleaſed the Diſſenters, only ſo far, as it gave them hopes that the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> might be preſerved; but they were afraid, leſt the King might remember their former promoting the <hi>Bill</hi> of <hi>Excluſion,</hi> and that thereby they ſhould not only continue under the laſhes of the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> Diſcipline, but of the Kings disfavour; and having yet the <hi>Idea's</hi> which had been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed into them of a <hi>Popiſh Succeſſor,</hi> and the D. of <hi>Monmouth</hi> giving them an opportunity to make head under the ſpecious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of preſerving the Proteſtant Religion, as many of them as were near the Scene of Action, and were fool-hardy, joyn'd with him in that Rebellion; and the wiſhes for his ſucceſs were not wanting in moſt of that Party.</p>
            <p>But that Rebellion being ſo ſpeedily, and almoſt miraculouſly ſuppreſſed, they fled to the Church of <hi>England</hi> for Protection, flocked to the Churches, perſonated a Conformity, and ſo cloſely mixed, that they now ſeemed one Body, and one Church.</p>
            <p>Some leading Men of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> finding this great acceſſion of ſtrength, and being deſirous entirely to win the Diſſenters over, thought it expedient to let them ſee, how much they had been miſtaken, in thinking them, in the matter of Exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to be going over to <hi>Rome,</hi> and being willing to wipe off the Calumny the Diſſenters had caſt upon them, as being Papiſts in Maſquerade, they began inſtantly to ſhew their utmoſt Zeal againſt the Kings Religion.</p>
            <p>When therefore, the King, purſuant to His Royal deſign, before-mentioned, required the taking off the <hi>Teſt</hi> and <hi>Penal Laws;</hi> many leading Men of the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſet themſelves to oppoſe the King in it, and from that day, the more they found the King preſs it, the more they ſhewed their reluctance. Suddenly, ſeveral Miniſters, able, or unable, to manage the diſpute with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> began to confirm their Auditors, in the Doctrine of the Proteſtant Religion, and to inſinuate the danger we were in to loſe it, as ſoon as the <hi>Teſt,</hi> and <hi>Penal Laws</hi> ſhould be repeal'd; they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100804:4"/>murmur'd, and repin'd at every favour ſhewn to Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, and none were ſo much applauded, as thoſe who loſt their places, upon their denial to concur with the King in his demands. They animated and encouraged one another to ſtand the ſhock, not thinking, perhaps, they had to deal with a more reſolved Prince, than ſome of His Predeceſſors; nor apprehending, or not willing to ſee, what publick benefit the King deſign'd to the body of His Subjects, by the Repeal; and in fine, began to purſue all the methods of male-contents, finding this the only way to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barras the King, hinder all His glorious deſigns for the publick, and render uſeleſs his eminent virtues, in not affording Him the opportunity of appearing like Himſelf, or rendring His Reign glorious; becauſe, they were unwilling, any thing Great ſhould be performed by a King, that was not of their Religion.</p>
            <p>All this, His Majeſty carefully obſerved, and being unwilling to act any thing, but according to Juſtice, and the Laws of the Land, He wiſely enquir'd into the extent of His legal power. He knew he was by the Statutes declared Supream Head of the Church in His Dominions, had undoubted Prerogatives, He might make uſe of, and a Diſpenſing Power; and ſo ſettled thoſe by judicial Proceedings.</p>
            <p>The King having now aſſerted His Sovereignty, he thought it reaſonable, to manifeſt to all His Subjects, that it was not the eaſe only of the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> he aim'd at, but that He intended His Clemency ſhould be as extenſive as His Empire: Firſt therefore, He publiſhed His General Pardon, (excepting ſome few perſons) and in the interim, ſhew'd His diſpleaſure againſt thoſe who ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed His great deſign of Repeal; and laſtly, publiſhed this <hi>Indulgence,</hi> wherein He layed open the paternal goodneſs, and benignity of His Soul; the method, of enriching His people, and a foundation of their concord during His Reign; and for ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Ages, by extirpating the cauſes of Animoſities, Heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burnings, Feuds, and Oppreſſions of His people, by any prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Party; abridging them of nothing uſed in their Religious Worſhip, but only, of the power of compelling any one to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity; and depriving every party of that Authority, of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſterial impoſing ſuch diſtinguiſhing and Excluding <hi>Teſts,</hi> as incapacitated His Subjects to ſerve Him, and the Government, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Allegiance, and every Free-Mans Liberty.</p>
            <p>One would rationally have thought, that no party ſhould have been wanting in their Thanks for ſo great a Grace and Favour, ſo much the greater, in that it was beſtowed by a Prince, from whom no ſuch largeſs of Royal Bounty was expected; not the Church
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100804:4"/>of <hi>England,</hi> ſince, in the body of the ſame Indulgence, ſo liberal a Proviſion was made for it; not the Diſſenters, who had the moſt viſible benefits; nor any elſe, who did not prefer the profits they had by the <hi>Penal</hi> mulcts impoſed, or the pleaſure of inflicting puniſhments upon thoſe who were obnoxious to Eccleſiaſtical Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, or the Laws for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was then a Party of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who, owning the Kings Eccleſiaſtical Supremacy, and His Prerogative, looked upon this as an Act of State, which the King might Exert at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, for the publick tranquillity of His Dominions; and thought it their duty to be truly thankful, that the King had ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly ſecured to them the Honors and Emoluments of the Church, and entirely left them the Cathedrals, the Churches, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits annexed to them.</p>
            <p>Another, and a major part of the ſame Church, was vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menty moved by the Declaration, murmur'd, that their former ſerives were ſlighted; that Diſſenters, who had unanimouſly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the Kings Succeſſion, and been Rebels as often as they had opportunity, were preferr'd before them; and ſuggeſted, that this was deſign'd to enlarge the <hi>Roman Catholick Church,</hi> and as a ſcourge to them; and though they never publickly urged it, yet it is moſt manifeſt, that the depriving them of the coercive power, (though all other parties were as much diſarmed of that, as They,) grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully contributed to their reluctance.</p>
            <p>The Conductors of their Affairs pitched upon two Expedients, as moſt effectual to hinder the Kings reaping any benefits to the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> by it. The one was, to ſecure the Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> from a complyance, by ſtiffly oppoſing the <hi>Repeal,</hi> and queſtioning the <hi>Diſpenſing Power:</hi> The ſecond, by diſſuading Diſſenters from ſeparating from the common intereſt (as it is called) of Proteſtants; or making any court to the King, in rendring any Tribute of Thanks for His Royal Grace to them.</p>
            <p>To Eſtab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſh this, conſultations are had; leading Men among the Diſſenters are treated with, great promiſes are made, that Perſecution againſt them ſhall ceaſe, if ever the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> return again to its former ſun-ſhine: Pamphlets from <hi>Holland,</hi> and at home, aggravate the fear of Popery, and of the deſtruction of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and not only declaim againſt the abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of all <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> but the Diſpenſing Power, likewiſe, as tending to the ſhaking all other Laws, even thoſe of Property; and this ſeems the deſign of your <hi>Letter,</hi> writ ſmoother than Dr. <hi>Burne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> or the Repreſentation, but with as little difference, as to deſign, as there is betwixt a Dagger in a wooden, or ſilver Scabbard.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100804:5"/>Sir, I muſt own, that the politeneſs of the Style, the ſharpneſs, and plauſibleneſs of the Arguments, will contribute more to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the eſtabliſhing ſuch Mens minds, who have the greateſt affection for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and equal averſion to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> than any thing Publiſhed hitherto. But in my judgement, you have mixed ſo much Varniſh, as a ſteady eye may eaſily diſcover what need you had of it.</p>
            <p>When we ſee a falling Star, we make no great remarks upon it, becauſe it happens ſo frequently, and how bright ſo ever it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd, we find nothing upon its fall, but a little jelly dropt from the Clouds. But when a Comet appears, it excites the curioſity of the learned, to enquire into its motion, the altitude of it; and by conſulting by-paſt-times, and conſidering what events hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened when ſuch appear'd before, to make ſome Prognoſticks of its effects.</p>
            <p>Your <hi>Letter</hi> is not to be looked upon as a ſhooting Star, or paper Kite, but a blazing Star, therefore deſerves a ſerious conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for whatever thoſe, formerly reputed meteors, did ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie, yours moſt evidently denotes an unquiet temper in thoſe of your perſuaſion, a ſtudious deſire in them to eſtrange the Hearts of Loyal Subjects from their Sovereign, a queſtioning His preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and a charging Him with overturning the Laws, and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to Rule Arbitrarily. This fills peoples minds with doubts, ſuſpicions and jealouſies, ſtrows flax all over the Kingdom, ready to be ſet on fire; when you, by your <hi>enflaming Eloquence,</hi> have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared Undertakers. Therefore, I think it the duty of all that Honour the King, and love their Country's peace, and tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, to examine the tendency, and prevent the evil effects of ſuch an Apparition.</p>
            <p>But to leave the Allegory, and conſider the <hi>Letter:</hi> As it is a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe penn'd with Art and Elegance, and beautified with orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Language, it is delightſom to be read; but when the ſcope of it is weighed, the factiouſneſs of it, under the ſmoothneſs of the periods, the unreaſonable poſtulatums, the fictitious ſuppoſitions, and the ſevere reflections upon the King and His Government; it becomes honeſt Men to enquire into thoſe poiſonous drugs, that are ſo artificially gilded, and provide Antidotes againſt them.</p>
            <p>There are many Thouſands of His Majeſties Subjects, both better able, and more at leiſure, and concerned to Animadvert upon your Letter; but upon the firſt reading, I found many incentives to urge me to it, when I ſaw ſuch miſ-interpretations of his Majeſties Honourable deſigns, his conduct ſo calumniated, ſuch dangerous innuendo's, ſuch endeavours to poyſon the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100804:5"/>of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in their Loyalty; the Arts to make them forfeit their Reputations with His Majeſty and the World, by alluring them to do every thing, that made former Diſſenters ſo abnoxious, and leading them in the ſame ſteps, with which they had trod the ſtage ſo tragical to themſelves, and the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>What I have writ was the reſult of my thoughts, e're I had read any Anſwer, except the firſt two that were made you, but by diſtance of place, and other intervening accidents, which hinder the communicating of it hath been ſtopped hirherto; and if the opinion ſome have, that it may be yet uſeful to ſome that may need repeated cautions and admonitions, to beware of being ſeduced by the plauſibleneſs of your Language, had not prevailed with me, I ſhould have totally ſuppreſſed it. Now that I may do you all poſſible right, I have inſerted the Letter entire, according to the different Paragraphs, and ſubjoyned mine, and do freely yield, your Column is that of the compoſit order, beautiful, though not ſtrong, and I hope that mine may be more ſolid, like the Dorick rather chuſing to render my Anſwer, according to my Capacity, (flattering my ſelf at leaſt in the good intention) ſincere and uſeful than florid or fallacious; deſiring all along, when I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> ſeverity, to be underſtood no ways, as cenſuring the Church as Author of thoſe Laws, nor queſtioning the prudence of the State in making Laws, which, according to the temperament of the times, the ſecurity of the publick peace, and it may be the deſire of Uniformity upon prudential grounds, our Kings thought fit to Enact. But in this great revolution, when our King thinks fit to try other meaſures, I humbly judge it the intereſt of all peaceable ſpirits, and dutiful Subjects, calmly to weigh His Majeſties Reaſons, and yeild to the Repeal of ſuch Laws, as cannot now be put in execution; and may, in all human probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, conduce much to the publick tranquility of the Nation. But I ſhall take an opportunity to ſpeak to this, after I have diſpatched what I have to ſay to your Letter; wherein I would not be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood to plead for the merits of Diſſenters, but to ſhew that they have no reaſon to quit their right in the Kings favour, tendered to them without their ſeeking, by any Arguments you have brought; nor that the Members of the Church of <hi>England</hi> ought to be ſo much diſquieted, that it is granted to them, ſince the Diſſenters thereby will be without all excuſe, if this make them not better Subjects. Nor think I, the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath reaſon to be ſo jealous of being overlaid by them, ſince the conſtitution of the Government of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is better adapted to the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, than either the Claſſical or Congregational way; and that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100804:6"/>the Roman Catholicks can ſo multiply as to ballance both, in my judgement, is to be reckoned among the portents of Nature, and I will ſooner believe a grain of the powder of projection can turn a Hundred pound of Lead to pure Gold, than that this can be effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in one Age, without a Divine Miracle; which, when wrought, none will be troubled at, that own an omnipotent Being, to whoſe guidance they do ſubmit themſelves.</p>
            <div type="opponents_letter_and_authors_reply">
               <div type="letter">
                  <head>THE <hi>LETTER.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>SInce Addreſſes are in faſhion, give me leave to make one to You. This is neither the effect of Fear, Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, or Reſentment; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you may be ſure it is ſincere: and for that Reaſon it may expect to be kindly received. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it will have power enough to Convince, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon the Reaſons, of which you are to judge; and upon your preparation of Mind, to be perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Truth, whenever it appeareth to you. It ought not to be the leſs welcom, for coming from a friendly Hand, one whoſe kindneſs to you is not leſſened by difference of Opinion, and who will not let his thoughts for the publick be ſo tyed or confined to this or that ſub-diviſion of Proteſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants, as to ſtifle the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which, beſides all
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100804:6"/>other Arguments, is at this time become ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to preſerve us.</p>
                  <p n="b">
                     <hi>(b)</hi> I am neither ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized nor provoked to ſee, that in the condition you were put into by the Laws, and the ill circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances you lay under, by having the Excluſion and Rebellion laid to your Charge, you were deſirous to make your ſelves leſs uneaſie and obnoxious to Authority. Men who are ſore run to the neareſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy with too much haſt, to conſider all the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences: Grains of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance are to be given, where Nature gives ſuch ſtrong Influences. When to Men under Sufferings it offereth Eaſe, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Pain will hardly allow time to examine the Remedies; and the ſtrongeſt reaſon can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gain a fair Audience from our Mind, whilſt ſo poſſeſſed, till the Smart is a little allayed.</p>
                  <p n="c">
                     <hi>(c)</hi> I do not know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Warmth that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally belongeth to New Friendſhips, may not make it a harder Task for me to perſuade you. It is like telling Lovers, in the beginning of their Joys, that they will in a little time have an End.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100804:7"/>Such an unwelcom Style doth not eaſily find cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit: but I will ſuppoſe you are not ſo far gone in your new Paſſion, but that you will <hi>Hear</hi> ſtill; and therefore I am under the leſs diſcouragement, when I offer to your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration two things.</p>
                  <p n="d">
                     <hi>(d)</hi> The <hi>firſt</hi> is, the cauſe you have to <hi>Suſpect</hi> your New-Friends. The <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond,</hi> the Duty incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent upon you, in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity and Prudence, not to hazard the Publick Safety, neither by deſire of Eaſe, nor of Revenge.</p>
                  <p n="e">
                     <hi>(e)</hi> To the <hi>firſt,</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſmooth Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage is now put on to engage you, theſe New Friends did not make you their Choice, but their Refuge: They have ever made their firſt Courtſhips to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and when they were rejected there, they made their Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to you in the ſecond place. The inſtances of this, might be given in all times. I do not repeat them, becauſe whatſoever's unneceſſary, muſt be tedious, the Truth of this Aſſertion being ſo plain, as not to admit a Diſpute. You cannot
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100804:7"/>thereforer reaſonably flat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter your ſelves, that there is an Inclination to you. They never pretended to allow you any Quarter, but to uſher in Liberty for themſelves under that ſhelter. I refer you to Mr. <hi>Coleman's Letters,</hi> and to the <hi>Journals</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> where you may be convinced, if you can be ſo miſtaken, as to doubt; nay, at this very hour, they can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forbear, in the height of their Courtſhip, to let fall hard words of you. So little is Nature to be reſtrained: it will ſtart out ſometimes, diſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſubmit to the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpation of Art, and Interest.</p>
                  <p n="f">(f) This Alliance, between <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility,</hi> is bringing together the Two moſt contrary things that are in the World. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth not only diſlike the allowing Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, but by its Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples it cannot do it. Wine is not more expreſly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to the <hi>Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,</hi> than giving Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks Liberty to the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts:</hi> They are no more
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100804:8"/>able to make good their Vows to you, then Men married before, and their Wives alive, can confirm their Contract with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The continuance of their kindneſs, would be a habit of ſin, of which they are to repent, and their Abſolution is to be had upon no other terms, than their promiſe to deſtroy you. You are therefore to be hugged now, only that you may be the better ſqueezed at another time. There muſt be ſomething ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, when the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſetteth up Bills, and offereth Plaiſters for tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences: By all that hath hitherto appeared, her skill in Chirurgery lieth chiefly in a quick Hand, to cut off Limbs; but ſhe is the worſt at Healing, of any that ever pretended to it.</p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:100804:8"/>
                  <p n="g">(g) To come ſo quick from another extream, is ſuch an unnatural mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that you ought to be upon your Guard; the other day you were <hi>Sons of Belial,</hi> now you are <hi>Angels of Light.</hi> This is a violent change, and it will be fit for you to pauſe upon it, before you believe it: If your fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are not altered, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is their opinion of you, what ever may be pretended. Do you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve leſs than you did, that there is Idolatry in the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> ſure you do not. See then, how they treat both in words and writing, thoſe that entertain that Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. Conclude from hence, how inconſiſtent their favour is with this ſingle Article, except they give you a Diſpenſation for this too, and by a <hi>Non Obſtante,</hi> ſecure you that they will not think the worſe of you.</p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:100804:9"/>
                  <p n="h">(h) Think a little how dangerous it is to build upon a Foundation of Parodoxes. Popery now is the only friend to Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the known Enemy to Perſecution: The men of <hi>Taunton</hi> and <hi>Tiver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> are above all other Eminent for Loyalty. The <hi>Quakers</hi> from being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by the Papiſts not to be Chriſtians, are now made Favourites, and taken into their particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Protection; they are on a ſudden grown the moſt accompliſhed men of the Kingdom in good Breeding, and give thanks with the beſt Grace in double refined Language. So that I ſhould not won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, though a man of that Perſuation: in ſpite of his Hat, I ſhould be Maſter of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. Not to ſay harſher words, theſe are ſuch very new things, that it is impoſſible not to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend our Belief, till by a little more Experience we may be inform'd whether they are Realities or Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritions: We have been under ſhameful miſtakes if theſe Opinions are true; but for the preſent, we are apt to be incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, except we could be convinced, that the Prieſts words in this Caſe too,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100804:9"/>are able to make ſuch a ſudden, and effectual Change; and that their Power is not limited to the Sacrament, but that it extendeth to alter the nature of all other things, as often as they are ſo diſpoſed.</p>
                  <p n="i">(i) Let me now ſpeak of the Inſtruments of your Friendſhip, and then leave you to judge, whether they do not afford matter of ſuſpicion. No ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is to be mingled where healing only is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended; ſo nothing will be ſaid to expoſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar men, how ſtrong ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Temptation may be, or how clear the Proofs to make it out. A word or two in general, for your better Caution, ſhall ſuffiee: Suppoſe then, for Argument's ſake, that the Mediators of this new Alliance, ſhould be ſuch as have been former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imployed in Treaties of the ſame kind, and there detected to have Acted by Order, and to have been Impowered to give Encouragement and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. Would not this be an Argument to ſuſpect them?</p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:100804:10"/>
                  <p n="k">(k) If they ſhould plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be under Engagements to one Side, their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the other, ought to be received according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; their fair Pretences are to be looked upon as part of their Commiſſion, which may not improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly give them a Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the caſe of Truth, when it may bring Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice upon the Service of thoſe by whom they are imployed.</p>
                  <p n="l">(l) If there ſhould be men who having formerly had Means and Authority to perſuade by Secular Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, have in purſuance of that Power, ſprinkled Mony amongſt the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Miniſters; and if thoſe very Men ſhould now have the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, practice the ſame Methods, and Disburſe, where they cannot other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe perſuade: It ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to me rather an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, than a Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Deceit.</p>
                  <p n="m">(m) If there ſhould be Ministers amongſt you, who by having fallen un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Temptations of this kind, are in ſome ſort engaged to continue their Frailty, by the awe they are in leaſt it ſhould be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100804:10"/>expoſed: The Perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of theſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Men muſt ſure have the leſs force, and their Arguments, though never ſo ſpecious, are to be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, when they come from Men who have Mortgaged themſelves to ſevere Creditors that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a rigorous obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Contract, let it be never ſo unwarran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabe.</p>
                  <p n="n">(n) If theſe, or any others ſhould at this time Preach up Anger and Vengeance againſt the Church of <hi>England:</hi> may it not, without Injuſtice, be Suſpected, that a thing ſo plainly out of ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſprings rather from corruption than miſtake; and that thoſe who act this cholerick part, do not believe themſelves, but only purſue higher Directions, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to make good that part of the contract which obligeth them, upon a Forfeiture, to make uſe of their inflaming Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence? They might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend their Wages would be retrenched, if they ſhould be Moderate: And therefore, whilſt Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence is their Intereſt, thoſe who have not the ſame Arguments, have
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100804:11"/>no reaſon to follow ſuch a Partial Example</p>
                  <p n="o">(o) If there ſhould be men who by the load of their Crimes againſt the Government, have been bowed down to comply with it againſt their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: who by incurring the want of a Pardon, have drawn upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the neceſſity of a Reſignation: Such men are to be lamented, but not to be believed. Nay, they themſelves when they have diſcharged their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwelcome Task, will be inwardly glad that their forced Endeavours do not ſucceed, and are pleas'd when men reſiſt their Inſinuations; which are far from being Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary or Sincere, but are Squeezed out of them by the weight of their being ſo Obnoxious.</p>
                  <p n="p">(p) If in the height of this great Dearneſs by comparing things, it ſhould happen, That at this inſtant, there is much a ſurer friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with thoſe who are ſo far from allowing Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100804:11"/>that they allow no Living to a Proteſtant under them. Let the Scene lie in what part of the World it will, the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will come home, and ſure it will afford ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ground to ſuſpect. Apparent Contradictions muſt ſtrike us: neither Nature nor Reaſon can digeſt them; Self-Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, and the deſire to deceive our ſelves, to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie a preſent Appetite, with all their Power, which is Great, cannot get the better of ſuch broad Conviction, as ſome things carry along with them. Will you call theſe vain and empty Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? have you been at all times ſo void of Fears and Jealouſies as to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie your being ſo unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably Valiant, in having none upon this occaſion? Such an extraordinary Courage at this unſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable time, to ſay no more, is too dangerous a Vertue to be commended.</p>
                  <p n="q">(q) If then for theſe and a thouſand other Reaſons, there is cauſe to ſuſpect, ſure your new Friends are not to Dict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate to you, or adviſe you; for inſtance, The Addreſſes that fly abroad every Week, and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther us with <hi>another to the ſame;</hi> the firſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100804:12"/>Draughts are made by thoſe who are not very proper to be Secretaries to the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; and it is your part only to Write them out fairer again. Strange! that you who have been formerly ſo much againſt <hi>Set forms,</hi> ſhould now be content the Priests ſhould Indite for you. The nature of Thanks is an unavoidable conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of being Pleaſed or Obliged; they grow in the Heart, and from thence ſhew themſelves either in Looks, Speech, Writing, or Action: No Man was ever thankful becauſe he was bid to be ſo; but becauſe he had, or Thought he had ſome Reaſon for it. If then there is cauſe in this <hi>Caſe</hi> to pay ſuch extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant acknowledgments, they will flow naturally, without taking <hi>ſuch</hi> pains to procure them; and 'tis unkindly done to tire all the Poſt-Horſes with car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying Circular Letters to Sollicite that which would be done without any Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or Conſtraint: If it is really in it ſelf ſuch a favour, what needeth ſo many preſſing men to be thankful, and with ſuch eager Circumſtances, that where perſwaſion cannot
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100804:12"/>delude, Threatnings are imployed to fright them into a compliance? Thanks muſt be Voluntary, not only <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nconstrained, but <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſollicited, elſe they are either Trifles or Snares, they either ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie nothing, or a great deal more than is inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by thoſe that give them. If an Inference ſhould be made, That whoſoever Thanketh the King for His <hi>Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> is by that engaged to juſtifie it in point of Law; it is a greater ſtride than, I preſume, all thoſe care to make who are perſuaded to Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs: If it ſhall be ſuppoſed, that all the Thankers ſhall be the Repealers of the <hi>TEST,</hi> when ever a <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhall meet. Such an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation is better pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented before, than diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed afterwards; and the ſureſt way to avoid the lying under ſuch a ſcandal, is not to do any thing that may give a colour to the miſtake: Theſe beſpoken Thanks are little leſs im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper than Love-Letters that were Sollicitated by the Lady to whom they are to be Directed; ſo, that beſides the little ground there is to give
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100804:13"/>them, the manner of getting them, doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly leſſen their Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue. It might be wiſhed that you would have ſuppreſsed your impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent for the ſake of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, to enjoy it within your ſelves, without the Liberty of a publick Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, till a Parliament had allowed it: But ſince that could not be, and that the Artifices of ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you have made uſe of the Well meant Zeal of the Generality to draw them into this miſtake; I am ſo far from blaming you with that ſharpneſs which, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, the matter in ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs would bear, that I am ready to err on the ſide of the more gentle conſtruction.</p>
                  <p n="r">(r) There is a great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> between enjoying quietly the advantages of an Act irregularly done by others, and the going about to ſupport it againſt the Laws in being; the Law is ſo Sacred, that no Treſpaſs againſt it is to be Defended; yet Frail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties may in ſome meaſure be Excuſed, when they cannot be Juſtified. The deſire of enjoying a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty from which men have been ſo long re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100804:13"/>may be a Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation that their Reaſon is not at all times able to reſiſt. If in ſuch a caſe, ſome Objections are leapt over, indifferent men will be more inclined to lament the Occaſion, than to fall too hard upon the Fault, whilſt it is covered with the Apologie of a good Intention; but where to reſcue your ſelves from the Severity of one Law, you give a blow to all the Laws, by which your Religion and Liberty are to be protected; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of ſilently receiving the benefit of this Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, you ſet up for Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates to ſupport it, you become voluntary Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors, and look like Counſel retained by the Prerogative againſt your old friend <hi>Magna Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> who hath done nothing to deſerve her falling thus under your Diſpleaſure.</p>
                  <p n="s">(s) If the caſe then ſhould be, that the Price expected from you for this Liberty, is giving up your Right in the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100804:14"/>Laws, ſure you will think twice, before you go any further in ſuch a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Bargain. After gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Thanks for the breach of one Law, you loſe the Right of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of the breach of all the reſt; you will not very well know how to defend your ſelves, when you are preſſed; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given up the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when it was for your advantage, you cannot recal it, when it ſhall be to your prejudice. If you will ſet up at one time a Power to help you, which at another time by parity of Reaſon ſhall be made uſe of to deſtroy you, you will neither be pitied, nor relieved againſt any miſchief you draw upon your ſelves, by being ſo unreaſonably thankful. It is like calling in Auxili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aries to help, who are ſtrong enough to ſubdue you: in ſuch a caſe your complaints will come too late to be heard, and your ſufferings will raiſe mirth inſtead of Compaſſion.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:100804:14"/>
                  <p n="t">
                     <hi>(t)</hi> If you think, for your excuſe, to expound your Thanks ſo as to reſtrain them as to this particular caſe; Others, for their end, will extend them further; and in theſe differing Interpretation, that which is back'd by Authority will be the moſt likely to prevail; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when by the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage you have given them, they have in truth the better of the Argument, and that the inferences from your own Conceſſions are very ſtrong, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs againſt you. This is ſo far from being a groundleſs Suppoſition, and there was a late in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100804:15"/>of it, the laſt Seſſion of Parliament, in the Houſe of Lords, where the firſt Thanks, though things of courſe, were interpreted to be the Approbation of the Kings whole Speech, and a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint never ſo much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked; and it was with difficulty obtained, not to be excluded from the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of objecting to this mighty Prerogative of Diſpenſing, meerly by this innocent and uſual piece of good Manners, by which no ſuch thing could poſſibly be intended.</p>
                  <p n="u">
                     <hi>(u)</hi> This ſheweth, that ſome bounds are to be put to your good Breeding, and that the Conſtitution of <hi>England</hi> is too valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able a thing to be ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon a Complement. Now that you have for ſome time enjoyed the benefit of the End, it is time for you to look into the danger of the Means: The ſame Reaſon that made you deſirous to get Liberty, muſt make you Sollicitous to preſerve it; ſo that the next thought
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100804:15"/>will naturally be, not to engage your ſelf beyond Retreat, and to agree ſo far with Principles of all Religions, as not to relie upon a Death-bed Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
                  <p n="x">
                     <hi>(x)</hi> There are certain Periods of Time, which being once paſt, make all Cautions ineffectual, and all Remedies deſperate. Our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings are apt to be hurried on by the firſt Heats; which, if not reſtrained in time, do not give us leave to look back, till it is too late. Conſider this in the caſe of your Anger againſt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and take warning by their Miſtake in the ſame kind, when after the late King's Reſtoration, they preſerved ſo long the bitter taſt of your rough uſage to them in other times, that it made them forget their Intereſt, and ſacrifice it to their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge.</p>
                  <p n="y">
                     <hi>(y)</hi> Either you will blame this Proceeding in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100804:16"/>them, and for that Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon not follow it, or if you allow it, you have no reaſon to be offended with them; ſo that you must either diſmiſs your Anger, or loſe your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe; except you ſhould argue more partially than will be ſuppoſed of men of your Morality and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding.</p>
                  <p n="z">
                     <hi>(z)</hi> If you had now to do with thoſe rigid Prelates, who made it matter of Conſcience to give you the leaſt Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, but kept you at an uncharitable diſtance, and even to your more reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Scruples continued ſtiff inexorable, the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument might be fairer on your ſide; but ſince the common Danger hath ſo laid open that Miſtake, that all the former Haughtineſs towards you is for ever extinguiſhed, and that it hath turned the Spirit of Perſecution, into a Spirit of a Peace, Charity, and Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſhall this happy Change only affect the Church of <hi>England?</hi> and are you ſo in love with Separation, as not to be moved by his Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple?
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100804:16"/>It ought to be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, were there no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon than that it is a Vertue; but when beſides that, it is become neceſſary to your preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, it is impoſſible to fail the having its effect upon you.</p>
                  <p n="a">
                     <hi>(a)</hi> If it ſhould be ſaid that the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is never Humble, but when ſhe is out of Power, and therefore loſeth the Right of being believed when ſhe preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to it; the Anſwer is, <hi>firſt,</hi> it would be an uncharitable Objection, and very much miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timed; an unſeaſonable Triumph, not only unge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous, but unſafe: So that in theſe Reſpects it cannot be urged, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Scandal, even though it could be ſaid with Truth. <hi>Secondly,</hi> This is not ſo in Fact, and the Argument muſt fall, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing built upon a falſe Foundation; for what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever may be told you, at this very hour, and in the heat and glare of your preſent Sun-ſhine, the Church of <hi>England</hi> can in a Moment bring Clouds again; and turn the Royal Thunder upon your Heads, blow you off the Stage with a Breath, if ſhe would give but a Smile for a kind Word;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100804:17"/>the leaſt Glimpſe of her Compliance, would throw you back into the ſtate of Suffering, and draw upon you all the Arrears of Severity, which have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crued during the time of this kindneſs to you, and yet the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> with all her Faults, will not allow her ſelf to be reſcu'd by ſuch unjuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable means, but chuſeth to bear the weight of power, rather than lie under the burthen of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Criminal.</p>
                  <p n="b">
                     <hi>(b)</hi> It cannot be ſaid, that ſhe is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nprovoked; Books and Letters come out every day, to call for Anſwers, yet ſhe will not be ſtirred. From the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100804:17"/>ſuppoſed Authors, and the ſtile one would ſwear they were <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakers, and had made a Contract to fall out with the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> There are Laſhes in every <hi>Addreſs,</hi> Challanges to draw the Pen in every Pamphlet; In ſhort, the faireſt occaſions in the World given to quarrel; but ſhe wiſely diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth between the Body of Diſſenters, whom ſhe will ſuppoſe to Act, as they do, with no ill intent; and theſe ſmall Skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes pickt and ſent out to picqueer, and to begin a Fray amongſt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, for the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, as well as the advantage of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="c">
                     <hi>(c)</hi> This conduct is ſo good, that it will be ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous not to Applaud it. It is not equal dealing, to blame our Adverſaries for doing ills and not commend them when they do well.</p>
                  <p n="d">
                     <hi>(d)</hi> To hate them becauſe they perſecuted, and not to be reconciled to be reconciled to them when they are ready to ſuffer, rather than receive all the Advantages, that can be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100804:18"/>gained by criminal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance, is a Principle no ſort of Chriſtians can own, ſince it would give an Objection to them never to be anſwered.</p>
                  <p n="e">
                     <hi>(e)</hi> Think a little, who they were that promoted your former Perſecutions, and then conſider how it will look to be angry with the Inſtruments, and at the ſame time to make a League with the Authors of our Sufferings.</p>
                  <p n="f">
                     <hi>(f)</hi> Have you enough conſidered what will be expected from you? Are you ready to ſtand in every Borough by Vertue of a <hi>Conge d'eſlire,</hi> and inſtead of Election, be ſatisfied if you are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned?</p>
                  <p n="g">
                     <hi>(g)</hi> Will you in <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> juſtifie the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing Power, with all its Conſequences, and Repeal the <hi>Teſt,</hi> by which you will make way for the Repeal of all the Laws, that were made to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve your Religion, and to Enact others that ſhall Deſtroy it?</p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:100804:18"/>
                  <p n="h">(h) Are you diſpoſed to change the Liberty of Debate, into the Merit of Obedience, and to be made Inſtruments to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal or Enact Laws, when the <hi>Roman Conſiſtory,</hi> are <hi>Lords of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="i">(i) Are you ſo linked with your new Friends, as to reject any <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi> a <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhall offer you, if it ſhall not be ſo Comprehenſive as to include the Papiſts in it.</p>
                  <p n="k">(k) Conſider that the implyed Conditions of our new Treaty are no leſs, then that you are to do every thing you are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, without examining, and that for this preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> your real Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is to be Sacrificed: Your former Faults hang like Chains ſtill about you, you are let looſe only vpon Bayl; the firſt Act of Non-compliance, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth you to Jayl again.</p>
                  <p n="l">
                     <hi>(l)</hi> You may ſee that the Papiſts themſelves do not rely upon the Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of this Power, which you are to Juſtifie, ſince the being ſo very earneſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:100804:19"/>to get it Eſtabliſhed by a Law, and the doing ſuch very hard things in order, as they think to obtain it, is a clear Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that they do not think that the ſingle power of the Crown is in this caſe a good Foundation; eſpecially when this is done under a Prince, ſo very tender of all the Rights of Sovereignty, that he would think it a diminution to his Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, where he concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth it ſtrong enough to go alone, to call in the Legiſlative help to ſtrengthen and ſupport it.</p>
                  <p n="m">
                     <hi>(m)</hi> You have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly blamed the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and not without reaſon, for going ſo far as they did in their compliance; and yet as ſoon as they ſtopped, you ſee they are not only De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, but Proſecuted: Conclude then from this Example, that you muſt either break off your Friendſhip, or reſolve to have no Bounds in it. If they do not ſucceed in their Deſign, they will leave you firſt; if they do, you must either leave them, when it will be too late for your Safety, or elſe after the ſqueaſines of ſtartling at a Surplice, you muſt be forced to ſwallow <hi>Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:100804:19"/>
                  <p n="n">
                     <hi>(n)</hi> Remember that the other day, thoſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> were <hi>Trimmers</hi> for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during you, and now by a ſudden Turn, you are become the Favourites; do not deceive your ſelves, it is not the Nature of laſting Plants thus to ſhoot up in the Night; you may look gay and green for a little time, but you want a Root to give you a continuance. It is not ſo long ſince, as to be forgotten, that the <hi>Maxim</hi> was, <hi>It is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for a Diſſenter, not to be a REBELL.</hi> Conſider at this time in <hi>France,</hi> even the new Converts are ſo far from being Imployed, that they are Diſarmed; their ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Change maketh them ſtill to be diſtruſted, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that they are Reconciled: What are you to expect from your dear Friends, to whom, when ever they ſhall think fit to throw you off again, you have in other times given ſuch Arguments for their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe?</p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:100804:20"/>
                  <p n="o">
                     <hi>(o)</hi> Beſides all this, you Act very unskilfully againſt your viſible Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest, if you throw away the Advantages, of which you can hardly fail in the next probable Revolution. Things tend naturally to what you would have, if you would let them alone, and not by an unſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Activity loſe the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences of your good Star, which promiſeth every thing that is proſperous.</p>
                  <p n="p">
                     <hi>(p)</hi> The Church of <hi>England</hi> convinced of its Errour in being Severe to you; the <hi>Parliament,</hi> whenever it meeteth, is ſure to be Gentle to you; the next Heir bred in the Country which you have ſo often Quoted for a Pattern of Indulgence; a general Agreement of all thinking Men, that we muſt no more cut our ſelves off from the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants abroad, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inlarge the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions upon which we are to build our Deſences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; ſo that in truth, all things ſeem to conſpire to give you eaſe and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, if by too much haſt to anticipate your good Fortune, you do not deſtroy it.</p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:100804:20"/>
                  <p n="q">
                     <hi>(q)</hi> The Proteſtants have but one Article of Humane Strength, to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Power which is now againſt them, and that is, not to loſe the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, by being ſo unwary as to let themſelves be divided.</p>
                  <p n="r">
                     <hi>(r)</hi> We all agree in our Duty to our Prince, our Octjections to his Belief, do not hinder us from ſeeing his Virtues; and our not complying with his Religion, hath no effect upon our Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance; we are not to be Laughed out of our Paſſive Obedience, and the Doctrine of <hi>Non-Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance,</hi> though even thoſe who perhaps owe the best part of their Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to that Principle, are apt to make a Jest on't.</p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:100804:21"/>
                  <p n="ſ">
                     <hi>(ſ)</hi> So that if we give no Advantage by the fatal Miſtake of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>applying our Anger, by the natural courſe of things, this Danger will paſs away like a ſhower of Hail; fair weather will ſucceed, as lowering as the Sky now looketh, and all by this plain and eaſie Receipt. Let us be ſtill, quiet, and undivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, firm at the ſame time to our Religion, our Loyalty, and our Laws, and ſo long as we conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue this Method, it is next to impoſſible, that the odds of two hundred to one ſhould loſe the Bet; except the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which hath been ſo long barren of Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, ſhould now in her declining Age, be brought to Bed of One that would out-do the best ſhe can brag of in her <hi>Legend.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="t">
                     <hi>(t)</hi> To conclude, the ſhort Question will be, Whether you will joyn with thoſe who muſt in the end run the ſame Fate with you. If Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of all ſorts in their behaviour to one another, have been to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:100804:21"/>blame, they are upon the more equal terms, and for that very reaſon it is fitter for them now to be Reconciled. Our Diſunion is not only a Reproach, but a danger to us; thoſe who believe in modern Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, have more Right, or at least more Excuſe, to neglect all Secular Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; but for us, it is as juſtifiable to have no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as wilfully to throw away the humane Means of preſerving it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="reply">
                  <head>THE REPLY.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IT is a moſt undeniable truth, that <hi>faſhionable</hi> Addreſſes are very little to be regarded; and the temper of the Nation as little to be known by them, as we can know Men to be of one inclination, becauſe they were one ſort of habit; but when they flow from Gratitude, Duty, and Intereſt, and not from <hi>fear</hi> or <hi>reſentment,</hi> they are good ſymbols of unconſtrainedneſs, and ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; and to whom ſoever preſented, ought to be kindly received.</p>
                  <p>I own not my ſelf a Diſſenter from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and upon that ſcore, find not my ſelf concerned in all that you write relating to them; but aſſure you, I am one of thoſe that have a propenſity of mind, ready to receive any impreſſion of Reaſon, and who am ſo ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that a great part of the comforts of humane Life, and Oeconomy of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is loſt, to thoſe who confine their Charity, good Eſteem and Candor to thoſe, only of their own <hi>Opinion:</hi> That you and I differ moſtly, in that you confine your thoughts for the <hi>publick,</hi> to the <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diviſion</hi> of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> only; whereas I think, they ought to be enlarged likewiſe to all Honourable Virtuous, and Loyal perſons of other denominations; and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100804:6"/>
                     <hi>Fear</hi> or <hi>Reſentment</hi> ought <hi>at this time,</hi> to make us ſwerve from that Golden Rule, of doing to others, as we would have others do to us.</p>
                  <p n="b">
                     <hi>(b)</hi> It is true, that in ſmall wounds, in the fleſhy parts only, the <hi>ſympathetick</hi> way of <hi>Cure,</hi> and cloſing the wound in its own blood with bandage of clean Linnen, will ſerve; but where <hi>amputations</hi> and <hi>lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations</hi> are ſuch (as Secluſion and Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion) ſovereign, wound, ſalves are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite. You allow your Diſſenter to act by natural inſtinct, as other Animals do that can lick themſelves whole, and you dreſs their wounds with ſo gentle a touch, as if you were unconcerned whether they were cur'd, or not; and leaſt they ſhould <hi>infandum renovare dolorem,</hi> reflect upon the freſh bleeding wounds, you give them a doſe of <hi>Opium:</hi> It is true, you blame the Patient for his precipitate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in uſing the <hi>Remedies neareſt</hi> at hand, without <hi>examining,</hi> not only the skill and ability, but the good intention of the Chirurgion, and the vertues of his <hi>Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies;</hi> but this is all Artifice, that you may get the Patient to commit himſelf to your care, and that you might poſſeſs him with an Opinion, that none elſe had the true method of healing, which is not fair practice, to decoy him from uſing the certaineſt and moſt aſſured help this Iſland can afford.</p>
                  <p n="c">
                     <hi>(c)</hi> Here you change the Scene, and transform your Patient into a paſſionate Wooer, who is fallen in love with a <hi>new Friend;</hi> and ſince you preſume it will be an hard task to make him quit his new Amours, for his late coy and ſcornful Lady; you are contriving a <hi>Faſcination,</hi> and would garniſh his <hi>Bridal Feast</hi> with a <hi>Mene Tekel,</hi> a <hi>Memento Mori,</hi> which ſhows (by your favour) an ill nature in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100804:7"/>you, that will not allow a Diſſenter the joy of his <hi>hony moon.</hi> In this, you are like one that after vows, perſuades to Enquires: But I hope e're I have gone through with this diſcourſe; you will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, though your <hi>Style</hi> is ſoft and beautiful, yet there is a weakneſs in your Reaſonings, will not eaſily prevail with a true diſſenter, who is not ſo <hi>far gone in his new paſſion,</hi> but that he will <hi>hear,</hi> and anſwer too.</p>
                  <p n="d">
                     <hi>(d)</hi> Since you quit your exhortatory <hi>Preface,</hi> which was penn'd to obtain Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and now will let us ſee your dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity at Argument. I ſhall endeavour to follow your method; owning you have choſen the fitteſt <hi>mediums,</hi> and if you could make them as convincing as plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fible, (which is now to be examined) you might expect many Proſelites.</p>
                  <p n="e">
                     <hi>(e)</hi> The Kings Juſtice and Honour was as conſpicuous as early, in his praiſes of, and promiſes to the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and I believe, in the upſhot, thoſe Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians will be found the worſt enemies to both, who made ſuch ill conſtructions of the Kings deſire of the Repeal. So that whatever the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath, or can ſuffer, may be aſcribed to their taking the matter by the wrong handle. But it is moſt evident, Diſſenters were then deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have a mutual ſhare of Liberty, ſince the King granted, <hi>noli proſequi's, inhibitions,</hi> and other <hi>relexations</hi> to them, as ſoon as he did to <hi>Roman Catholicks.</hi> How dutiful it was to reject the Kings <hi>Courtſhip,</hi> I leave to all un-intereſſed perſons to judge, and the more the <hi>Inſtances</hi> can be multiplied, the greater is the demonſtration of the Kings deſire to preſerve them in their Duty; and the more faulty, thoſe Men who filled peoples minds with the affrightments of the Kings deſign to ſettle
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100804:7"/>Popery, and deſtroy the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which they knew morally impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and yet continue to make it the only <hi>Helmet Argument.</hi> Thoſe who fly to any for <hi>Refuge,</hi> had need uſe better Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments than <hi>flattery:</hi> whilſt Diſſenters were Rebells, they could expect no other Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the Law preſcribed, if the King had not been moſt merciful; and it is moſt apparent, a greater cauſe of the granting <hi>Indulgence,</hi> is to take away all occaſions and pretences of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> rather, than ſingly to uſher in Liberty to <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholicks,</hi> by that Grace. Neither is it any new inclination in the King to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve Diſſenters in Communion with the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> unleſs you will give him the lie, who ſo publickly avows, that it <hi>hath been ever his judgment, that none ought to be Oppreſſed and Perſecuted for matters of Religion;</hi> and I think He ought to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved as ſoon as any in His Kingdom. Therefore, if any <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> at this time, <hi>let fall hard words</hi> againſt Diſſenters, it can be againſt none but ſuch, who they have reaſon to ſuſpect, do act by no publick ſpirit of preſervation, for any but their own party; and by this ſhow, that they have not changed their Nature, by the favour that is afforded them.</p>
                  <p n="f">
                     <hi>(f)</hi> After all the ſearch I can make, I neither find it to be an Article of Faith in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to deny <hi>Liberty</hi> to, nor that Faith is not to be kept with <hi>Hereticks;</hi> and if any Conſtitution, or Decree of a Council be found to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that obligeth not <hi>Catholicks</hi> in point of <hi>Obedience.</hi> The fallacy of your reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is eaſily detected, by pulling out one pin the whole Machine flies in pieces. One cannot be a Member in <hi>Communion</hi> with the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or any other conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted Church, (whether Fallible, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible) who is by that Church declared a <hi>Heretick;</hi> ſo that liberty of Communion, is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100804:8"/>only what is inconſiſtent with the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> but it no ways follows, that <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> or <hi>Hereticks,</hi> in their ſenſe, ought not to be tollerated to Live; yea, enjoy their Worſhip, by the power of the Prince who grants that <hi>Indulgence</hi> as Father of his Country: For it is no Church Memberſhip that is required by <hi>Tolleration.</hi> Suppoſe any Prince, <hi>(let the Scene be where it will,)</hi> that hath in his Kingdom great numbers of Subjects, of ſeveral perſuaſions in Religion; muſt he unpeople his Kingdom of Two Hundred of his Subjects, for every ſingle Man of his own Religion, according to your Calculation? Do you judge in good ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, His Ghoſtly Father, or his Holy Father the <hi>Pope,</hi> will judge him to be in an habit of ſin for it, or enjoyn him for a Pennance, to make ſuch a Carnage? no, ſurely they will rather let the Tares grow among the Wheat; or if He do not this, muſt he pull ruine upon Himſelf, and all thoſe of His perſuaſion? How <hi>Infallible</hi> ſoever the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> may judge it ſelf, yet you muſt allow ſhe is not quite void of Senſe, Prudence, and humane Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, or will not in ſeveral things yield to publick good and neceſſity. You muſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that Church to oblige that King to a <hi>Barbariſm,</hi> even impoſſible in it ſelf to be effected, e're you can make good any ſuch concluſion from the Premiſes. Excommunication is the higheſt, and moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Sentence, any Church can pronounce; and it is to avoid Mutulations, Diſmembring, Inciſions, and Corroſives for Religion our merciful King propoſeth this Repeal, ſince it hath been by too ſad experience found, how Magiſtrates (Members of other Churches, beſides that of <hi>Rome</hi>) have been guilty of the ſame, whether with better <hi>Dexterity, Succeſs,</hi> or <hi>Authority,</hi> I now diſpute not; but ſurely all this harangue, tends rather to engage Diſſenters, at any rate, to purchaſe that Sovereign <hi>Panacaea,</hi> which will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Perſecution from any hand, than to continue in a ſtate of danger.</p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:100804:8"/>
                  <p n="g">
                     <hi>(g)</hi> Kings as well as others may Time matters, and the <hi>Indulgence</hi> of a Prince makes no quicker a change in a Diſſenter, than a <hi>Pardon</hi> doth after the Malefactor hath his Irons on, or the Halter about his neck, or the poor Man made inſtantly rich, by finding a Treaſure. Theſe motions are from <hi>extreames</hi> as quick, and as ſurprizing. Diſſenters, while under the ſenſe of continual ſufferings, might be inſtigated to <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and ſo be <hi>Sons of Belial;</hi> yet this ſacred Ray (if ſuch miſts as you are caſting before them hinder not) may well transform them to thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and dutiful Subjects, which is all that is expected. It is true, if the Diſſenters <hi>Features</hi> be not changed, from having a ſower, ſullen, murmuring, and repining Aſpect, to that of chearfullneſs, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titute; <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> have no reaſon to harbour a good Opinion of them: Or if they be ſuch Bigots, to charge all perſons that are not of their perſuaſion, with <hi>Idolatry,</hi> (as you know they have done to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> even by that Churches own Argument,) they are to be inſtructed better, but this hinders not the King to do them good, even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their deſerts; and I think it one of the greater Arguments, that you are a moſt Rigid <hi>Calviniſt;</hi> or <hi>Browniſt,</hi> rather than a Church of <hi>England</hi>-Man, that make uſe of this Article, and that you are a moſt undutiful Subject, that will brand your Sovereign with being an <hi>Idolater.</hi> So that if there were no other Reaſon; for that ſingle inference, every Loyal Subject ſhould be for Repealing the <hi>Test;</hi> and be ſo far from diſpenſing with any Diſſenter for broaching this Doctrine, (which might tempt ſome judaizing Zealots to ſtone him) that <hi>non obſtente,</hi> all the <hi>Indulgence;</hi> they ſhould be proceeded againſt as enemies to the Kings Crown and Dignity; and that ſhould be all you ſhould get by ridiculing ſuch words as the Kings Prerogative impowers him to uſe.</p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:100804:9"/>
                  <p n="h">
                     <hi>(h)</hi> That ſelf-preſervation may cauſe agreement of ſeveral intereſts to diſarm a common Perſecutor, is no Paradox; or that the men of <hi>Taunton</hi> and <hi>Tiverton</hi> ſhall become Loyal, when the prime ground of their diſloyalty is taken away; nor that in this comprehenſive liberty the <hi>Quakers</hi> (though no <hi>Chriſtians</hi> with ſome, who may object <hi>Antichriſtianity</hi> againſt others) ſhould not be conſidered. For in the Kings <hi>Indulgence</hi> the Subjects are not conſidered, as conforming to Canons and Conſtitutions of Churches, but as obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, grateful, or uſeful and induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Surely in a populous maritine City, we wonder not; nor is it thought inconvenient, that <hi>Turks,</hi> and <hi>Jews, Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, Abyſſines, Japanners,</hi> or <hi>Perſions, Italians, French,</hi> or <hi>Spaniards,</hi> or any other remote Nations, frequent the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> and exerciſe their ſeveral Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, provided they enrich it by Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick; and it is a much pleaſinger ſight, than to ſee the ſtreets thronged with beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars in as differently patched Coats, ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding one uniform doleful note of want, to cauſe pity and compaſſion. It is moſt true, that if a <hi>Popiſh Succeſſor</hi> were in reality ſuch a one, as he was ſometimes repreſented, we ſhould need to <hi>ſuſpend</hi> our <hi>belief</hi> of his Clemency, and that we have been under moſt <hi>ſhameful,</hi> and <hi>I</hi> may ſay of too many, even <hi>wilful miſtakes,</hi> concerning our Royal Sovereign, is a moſt demonſtrable truth; and ſince He gives ſo many Arguments, that it is not for the bringing in of Popery, but for the ſecuring, not only His <hi>Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks,</hi> but of all His other Subjects, from the laſh of <hi>Penal. Laws,</hi> that he grants this <hi>Indulgence;</hi> whereby all Induſtrious peaceable Men, may follow their imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments without being obnoxious to Fines,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100804:9"/>Impriſonments, or Death, for want of Uniformity: It will not ſurely be the Queſtion, Whether the <hi>Prieſts words</hi> of Conſecration, can Annihilate the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Bread; but whether it be more Kingly, for our Sovereign to feed His whole Family, or ſtarve ſome, whilſt others are too much pamper'd. It is not the myſtery of the Sacrament, ſo much troubles ſome, as it is, that a <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> King ſhould have more kindneſs for Proteſtant Diſſenters, than thoſe who would be eſteemed the zealouſeſt for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> can afford them.</p>
                  <p n="i">
                     <hi>(i)</hi> Mens heads are much eaſilier la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with, then unladen of ſuſpicions; how light ſoever they be, they generally Ballaſt the Veſſel; and where ever jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie enters, with it, croud in Legions of evil Spirits. If one had as many eyes as <hi>Pores,</hi> it would fit them all with deſtain'd Optick Glaſſes, or Priſmes, to give de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful Colours to every Object. And that which is moſt troubleſom, in this paſſion, is, that it is with great difficulty maſter'd; eſpecially when it is heightned by Intereſt. You have a great dexterity to improve this, by Affrightment, Calumny, and Detraction; which you couch in ſuch General Terms, as it is difficult to get a graſp of them. Therefore, I muſt paſs by what is Common place, and tell you, that a Secretary of the Cabals of the Uſurpers, or to the famous E. of <hi>Shafts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> could not have given a livelier De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the Imployment of theſe Emiſſaries, than you have done; but you do wifely not to <hi>expoſe</hi> perſons, leſt we ſhould know who they are, that are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd on the errand, which is only to alienate the Subjects Affections from their Sovereign, and to excite the peoples jealouſie. If any be imploy'd that have been detected, and are now ſincere, they are fitter to diſcover the former methods, for being wedges of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100804:10"/>ſame wood, they are fitteſt for the work of pinning or cleaving. But to hang a ſcandal in the Air like a Cloud, that none can know where the ſhower may fall, is not done like a Gentleman of your <hi>Morality</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="k">
                     <hi>(k)</hi> This character of a Juggler is ſo drawn to the life, that one would ſwear you were looking all the while in the Glaſs, while you uſed the Pencil. Diſſimulation is ſuch a changling, that it is all Vizard-mask, with ſeveral foyles ſeperable by ſleight of hand; ſo that one may ſooner find Faith in an <hi>Affrican,</hi> than in ſuch a ſhift-coat. But till you can prove ſuch are <hi>Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated</hi> to work Diſſenters to comply with the King, all the Water runs but by the Mill.</p>
                  <p n="l">
                     <hi>(l)</hi> That there are mercinary Men, is no ſuch News, that need be told with ſuch cumlocution. Thoſe that uſe ſuch tools, will find them often need the whetting, and they muſt be vain ſpend-thrifts, (which I think you cannot ſay of our King;) that pour their Mony into a bottomlels purſe. <hi>Oates, Ignoramus Juries,</hi> and penſionary witneſſes, were more proper Cattle to be fed with ſuch Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, than Diſſenting Miniſters, if I be not miſtaken in them. The King neither needs, nor will ever imploy ſuch Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. He knows better how to manage his Exchequer, than to waſte it on ſuch Hirelings, who ſell their Conſcience and Service by inch of Candle.</p>
                  <p n="m">
                     <hi>(m)</hi> From Eye-witneſſes, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributors themſelves; I have heard, that ſeveral <hi>Charities</hi> to <hi>Non-conformiſt</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, were put under their Preaching Cuſhions; and I do not much wonder, that theſe Benevolences (which were as good as <hi>Glebe</hi> and <hi>Tithe</hi>) enabled them to reſiſt the Temptation of taking Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100804:10"/>with the condition of renouncing the Covenant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But that there ſhould be any among them now, who, for ſuch filthy lucre, deſign to <hi>Morigage</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, (which you muſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, or nothing,) I ſhall never believe upon your bare ſuggeſtion. In former times by keeping up the Schiſm, they might hope for ſome favourable Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, whereby they might be capable of liberal Maintenance; but that the <hi>Rigor</hi> of their <hi>Creditors</hi> ſhall drive them to put on the <hi>Cowl</hi> or <hi>Scapular,</hi> or co-ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate with thoſe that deſign it, ſhall be no Article of my Faith.</p>
                  <p n="n">
                     <hi>(n)</hi> It ſeems you were ſenſible of the weakneſs of this <hi>Medium,</hi> and now the Diſſenters muſt Preach the Goſpel for envy. The forward Miniſters amongſt them are much obliged to you, ſince it ſeems they are either <hi>Judas's</hi> to ſell the Cauſe for Silver, or muſt be branded with one of the Devils Characters, Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers of the Brethren; and whether you leſſen their crimes in ſaying thoſe who act this <hi>Cholerick part, believe not themſelves;</hi> but therein ſin againſt their Conſciences, and only <hi>purſue higher directions;</hi> I leave to others to judge. What wages ſuch may get here, they beſt know: But I think it muſt be a ſevere puniſhment they may expect hereafter. May we not be more charitable to judge, that ſuch Men are ſo far from perſonating a <hi>Vengeance,</hi> and uſing fiery Tongues and <hi>inflaming Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence,</hi> for that end. That they only expreſs their reſentment againſt thoſe, who in their Apprehenſions have too ſeverely Perſecuted them for Conſcience-ſake. Such a Plea may be as like to gain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, as your too groundleſs Accuſation of them; for Indulgence, Charity, and Moderation, are very conſiſtent. The
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100804:11"/>King deſires all may enjoy their Religion in peace, and hires none to keep up the ſtrife by recrimination and violence, nor deſigns by the taking away of <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> that one Subject ſhould worry another; and therein gives you, as well as Diſſenters, a Gracious <hi>Preſident</hi> and <hi>Example</hi> to follow.</p>
                  <p n="o">
                     <hi>(o)</hi> Here, in my Opinion, you have expoſed your friends ſomething diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagiouſly. It is an unfortunate thing for any to have combin'd againſt the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, ſince it requires much tryal, e're their Repentance can be believ'd. It is true, thoſe that have had the Ric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, are found often to have a good ſhare of cunning and wit, but by their <hi>bowed</hi> Legs, or ſome other infirm parts, eſpecially in the region of their breaſt, they are eaſily diſtinguiſhed from thoſe of more healthy Conſtitutions. The old Proverb is as often true, of haſty Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts, as of Pardoned Perſons, <hi>That ſave a Thief from the Gallows, and he will be the firſt will do you a miſchief.</hi> But God forbid all ſhould be cenſur'd for ſome Mens double-fac'd Villanies. Such Sycophants ſhall never find me their Advocate; let every Herring hang by his own Tayl. Let thoſe who are <hi>detected,</hi> forfeit their neck, or hang by it in the Pillory, e're I pity them. But what I pray do thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, who never wore ſhackles, or were <hi>bowed down</hi> e're they comply'd, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to their Prince ſtrenuous endeavours for His Service, and that they will not fail to hit the mark; and yet deſignedly ſhoot ſhort, or over.</p>
                  <p n="p">
                     <hi>(p)</hi> It is an unhappy ſtate of Kings, that when they endeavour by good Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods, the eaſe and profit of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; yet they muſt be traduced by the inſolent Pens of malevolent Subjects. Our Gracious King hath afforded a ſafe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat, and Liberal Contributions to the Reffugees, whom the great neighbouring
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100804:11"/>Monarch hath Exiled; and by His Royal Enterpriſe, to get the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal'd, deſigns not only His Dominious to be free from all Perſecution for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but to be a ſafe harbor for the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſed; and is thereby taking the moſt contrary meaſures to what that neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Prince hath done. With what effrontry therefore, can you charge the King, either with imitating His exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or correſponding with him in that deſign? I Appeal to the fled Proteſtants, whether they find not as good uſage here, as any in their condition do in other Countries? which, methinks carries <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction broad enough,</hi> that <hi>you</hi> are a very evil Caluminator. It is true, there was a time, when the belief of Ten Thouſand <hi>Pilgrims</hi> and <hi>Black Bills,</hi> were endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to be crammed down our throats; and ſome were ſuch Cowards then, as to be frighted with them. Muſt we therefore be always Impos'd upon, and never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to our ſenſes again. The frequent diſcoveries of thoſe Impoſtures, cannot but recruit the moſt timerous Spirits, and reſtore them to ſome degree of <hi>valour,</hi> though it will deſerve no great <hi>Commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as a Vertue,</hi> ſince the thick miſt is ſo exhaled, which made us take a crop of Thiſtles, for a Battalion of Pikes.</p>
                  <p n="q">
                     <hi>(q)</hi> Amongſt a Hundred of your florid Sentences, I have not yet found one ſolid Reaſon, why Diſſenters ſhould not act as they do in policy, or that they want any Advice or <hi>Dictator,</hi> when they follow the conduct of their own Intereſt. They need not go down to thoſe ſome call Philiſtines, to whet their Weapons, which are only praiſes and thanks; which the pooreſt Beggar, without any touch of <hi>good bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> knows how to pay for a ſmall Alms.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100804:12"/>There was a time, when <hi>Petitions,</hi> (the Elder Brothers of <hi>Addreſſes</hi>) being formed by the leading Men of the Lower Houſe, were poſted into confiding Hands, to be ſent back Ten, or Twenty Thouſand ſtrong: Thoſe tended to the ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the hands of the <hi>Murtherers</hi> of the King; and you would now <hi>ſtint a ſpirit</hi> of Obedience and Thankfulneſs to our King, which ſprings and flows from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and obligation, and may be eaſily diſcover'd to be ſincere, in all the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Speeches, Writings, and Actions, and are ſo far from needing to be <hi>bid,</hi> that all your Rhetorick cannot forbid them. Surely you think not their Thanks to ſpring like Muſhroms without root, and in a Night. And if you will not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Diſſenters among the Tribe of think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Animals, yet let them have the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of ſenſitive Plants, that ſhrink at a rough touch, and erect their Leaves by a warmer Gleam: I ſee not therefore, why Diſſenters, having the ſenſe of former ſharp uſage, ſhould not perceive their eaſe, and whence it comes; and have no reaſon to queſtion their ſincerity of thanks, ſince they are for a matter of greateſt import to them they ever receiv'd from the Crown, ſince they ſub-divided from the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Yet I believe, there hath been more Induſtry us'd to Diſperſe ſuch Letters, as yours of <hi>Caution</hi> and <hi>Circumſpection,</hi> then ever there was for thoſe <hi>Circular</hi> ones of three or four Biſhops, and you are the firſt <hi>Poſt</hi> that brings the News of any that were <hi>threatn'd</hi> to joyn with them, or any <hi>affright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> us'd to cauſe a <hi>compliance,</hi> ſince they carry with them all the tokens of <hi>Volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarineſs, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nconſtrainedneſs,</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſolicitude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> that could be expected. Therefore, becauſe in good earneſt you think they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100804:12"/>will ſignifie a <hi>great deal,</hi> you are at all this pains. If that which Diſſenters have ſo earneſtly deſn'd, pray'd, yea, fought for, can be called a <hi>Triſte,</hi> you are in the right. I never thought Addreſſors ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle acquainted with the <hi>Conſtitution of the Government,</hi> as to think their Addreſſes equal to Votes in Parliament, or that they, with the Kings aſſent, conſtituted the Legiſlative; though they may hope, ſuch Votes out of the Houſe, may beget others in it. I do not think any one, that had a piece of Gold given him, would be ſo beſotted to refuſe it, till he had conſulted ſuch a ſcrupulous Gentleman as you, whether it were all juſt in weight and allay, or that the giver came honeſtly by it. I ſuppoſe you are angry the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters made not their Addreſſes in this form.</p>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>Great SIR,</salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>WE would thank You for Your Gracious Declaration; but we know not, whether the Law impowers You to grant it; we have heard indeed of Your Majeſties having the excecutive part of the Laws in Your Royal Perſon, and the <hi>Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Power;</hi> and that You deſire the <hi>Teſt</hi> and <hi>Penal Laws</hi> may be aboliſhed by Act of Parliament. But before we return You our Thanks for the eaſe You afford us, or that we can reſolve to give our Voices for ſuch Repeal, we deſire to conſult our common Lawyers, and our Elder Brethren the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and then we will give You our Opinion; and we do this the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, leaſt you be miſtaken in us. <hi>Sir,</hi> we dare not encourage You to be kind to us; and we muſt ſtay our Addreſſes of thanks, leſt we give a <hi>Scandal</hi> to our
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100804:13"/>Brethren or they hereafter puniſh us, for this forwardneſs.</p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <p>I fancy you have the vanity to hope that your <hi>Letter</hi> will prevail with ſome to deſiſt from Addreſſes, upon thoſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives; otherwiſe, what need was there for you to be ſo urgent with them to <hi>ſuppreſs</hi> their <hi>impatience,</hi> and for the ſake of thoſe, that are now Abhorrers, to ſtick cloſe to the Act of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> till the King die, (whom God long preſerve to finiſh this great work;) in hopes a Proteſtant Parliament, under a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant King, will grant them better Terms: For I hope, by the word Parliament, you mean not the Two Houſes, like thoſe of 41, who Entitled them to the Supream Power. It ſeems, if Diſſenters hearken not to you, though at preſent you are willing to make a <hi>gentle Conſtruction,</hi> of the <hi>well meant Zeal</hi> of ſome, in <hi>drawing others into the Miſtake;</hi> yet you threaten them with <hi>Sharpneſs</hi> and <hi>Satyr,</hi> becauſe in <hi>ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the matter will bear it,</hi> if we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve you.</p>
                  <p n="r">
                     <hi>(r)</hi> It ſeems a Diſſenter may feed fully, but muſt ſay no Grace, or cry Roaſt-meat; would you have them pet like froward Children, becauſe the Benevolence was not offer'd firſt to them, or in the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances they deſire it. It ſeems, they may privately thank God for putting it into the Kings Heart, to grant them eaſe; yea, they may <hi>enjoy the Advantag e</hi> of it, but without noiſe, leſt ſome Dog catch the Morſel the Cat purs upon. Oh! a publick owning, and deſire to have <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi> Eſtabllſh'd by Law, is to <hi>ſupport an Act irregularly done</hi> againſt the ſacred <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land: This is ſuch a <hi>Treſpaſs,</hi> as may no ways be defended; but to obſerve
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100804:13"/>any rules of good manners or dutifulneſs to the King, is a grievous fault. Methinks you ought to have brought very undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Authorities, e're you had preſumed to queſtion the judgement of the King, His Privy Council, and the Court of the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> as to the <hi>Diſpenſing Power.</hi> But ſince you offer not one Syllable of Argument, I ſhall remit you to <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-Hall</hi> to defend the point and receive your doom. You endeavour gent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y to ſtroke the Diſſenters, that are under <hi>Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>Frailties,</hi> which makes them, you ſay, <hi>leap over the Objections</hi> may be made, and overlook the ſad conſequence of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thanks, not only as an inlet to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, but the giving a deadly <hi>blow</hi> to all <hi>the Laws,</hi> by which their <hi>Liberty and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion are to be protected.</hi> This is an heavy Sentence; whereby they are judg'd to ſell their Birth-right for a morſel of Bread, or a meſs of Pottage. Let us therefore turn the <hi>Optick</hi> Glaſs, and you may more ſurely diſcover, that the King deſigns no breach of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> nor to <hi>retain any Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil for the Prerogative</hi> againſt it; but on the contrary, to have it confirmed in a much larger extent, than ever it was by His Royal Predeceſſors: for it is moſt certain, that all <hi>Penal Laws</hi> for Religion are ſo many infringments of it; and if you would have <hi>Magna Charta</hi> inviolably kept, you know what Church is thereby Eſtabliſh'd. Here therefore you quarrel with the King, for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to have a Charter of <hi>Liberties</hi> Eſtabliſh'd, that will be a ſtandard for all future freedom, and enfranchiſement of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; and to infer, that the Subjects yielding to this, will put them out of the protection of all the Laws that ſecure their <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties,</hi> is no leſs an ignorant than ſeditious Suggeſtion.</p>
                  <p n="s">
                     <hi>(s)</hi> We are a moſt happy people, in the ſecurity we have by Law to enjoy the <hi>Liberties</hi> the Royal Predeceſſors of our moſt Gracious King hath granted. But if His Majecty effect His deſire in this
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100804:14"/>Repeal, He will be the Author of a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter freedom to the Subjects, then they ever yet enjoyed; ſo that none, in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, ſhall be put upon ever <hi>Complaining</hi> againſt, or the giving <hi>up the Queſtion;</hi> ſince all pretences of <hi>puttng</hi> it, will be thereby prevented. By the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating power of ſuch an Act, ſuch a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual aſſurance, and ſecurity would be given, as it would be in no parties power to endevour, or to deſire to <hi>miſchief,</hi> or <hi>destroy</hi> another. I fancy indeed, ſome Apparators and Bailifs may ſuffer a dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution of profit; and ſome men of vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicative ſpirits, may want the aſſiſtance of <hi>ſanguinary,</hi> and <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> to revenge themſelves by: But the benefit that will redound to the whole, will ſufficiently compenſate that loſs. The Kings of <hi>England</hi> will be the gainers, in that they will be no more diſquieted with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions upon the account of Religion. The Parliaments will be eaſed of the tire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, diſquieting, and unpleaſing toyl of making Laws, upon every emergence to reſtrain ſome party or other from their way of Worſhip; and impoſing <hi>Teſts</hi> and <hi>Oaths,</hi> according as prevailing Parties have power: and when the inteſtine ſtruggles of every party, to manacle, and put the ſhackles and badges of ſlavery, upon each other, ſhall be taken away; the Legiſlative will be at full liberty to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſoly the aggrandizing of our Kings, and reſtoring them to the power and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt at home and abroad, of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſeſt of their Predeceſſors: And to make good Laws for the enriching of the body of the people, and by perpetual harmony, unite the Subjects in the common band of Duty and Allegiance to their Sovereign, and mutual love and endearment to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> would have no occaſion to repine, ſince they might freely enjoy their Religion, and the Church of <hi>England</hi> would be poſſeſs'd of the Dignities and Benefices they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100804:14"/>enjoy; and the Diſſenters would be ſatisfied, that they had the freedom of their Tabernacles and Conventicles, and all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of this would be heightned in the peaceable and durable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of it; when it would be in no Parties power to invade the Liberties of another. This is the right Scheme of His Majeſties generous deſign; and if Diſſenters fall not to their old work of ſtubbing up Epiſcopacy, root and branch, it may moſt certainly continue. For the obedience of <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> under a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Government, we have the moſt near and compleat inſtance in the United Provinces, where they live with the free exerciſe of their Religion, under a Biſhop of their own, who is Treated ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Character by the States, to whom they impart their pleaſure; and by his directions the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> obey. So, that when the King of <hi>France</hi> Invaded that Country, none ſtood firmer than They did. Theſe pay ſuch an abſolute Obedience, that if the States, ſhould for a time interdict them the uſe of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, they would yield to it. So that all you urge as conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of the Repeal, vaniſheth upon the very opening the Kings intentions; which, I dare venture my head, that I have more truly declared, than You by all your ſmooth Oratory, have made out by ſuſpicions.</p>
                  <p n="t">
                     <hi>(t)</hi> Expounding of the ſenſe, and meaning of Oaths, is generally granted peculiarly to belong to the impoſer; and if the taker ſatisfie his Conſcience, and perform all required in the taking of them; the Civil Power enquires no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But in the return of thanks, the receivers of the Benefit, are the beſt Judges, in what ſenſe they render them; and I know not how they are concern'd in any Inferences, unleſs of thoſe that ſcruple their reality. It is true, if Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters only dream'd of an happineſs, they might conſult you for the <hi>Interpretations,</hi> but whilſt their eyes are open, and they have the full ſenſe of repoſe and eaſe, they muſt beg you will ſpare your <hi>Divinations,</hi> being reſolv'd to rely upon the kindneſs and Authority of the Giver, and will never be afraid of any <hi>Inferences,</hi> when it is ſo manifeſt, that His Majeſty deſigns common eaſe, and a perpetual ſettlement
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100804:15"/>of it, by Act of Parliament, which they think they have all the reaſon in the World to <hi>endeavour,</hi> may be effected in His Majeſties Reign, who laid the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of ſuch a Temple of Concord, as none of His Royal Predeceſſors ever did before. As to the ridiculing ſome Loyal perſons Zeal, to have had a favourable ſenſe put upon the thanks return'd for the Kings Gracious <hi>Speech;</hi> if there had been more of the Members of both Houſes, who would have credited the Kings Royal deſire to have been, juſt and equitable, and reflected upon the true Reaſons the King had to inſiſt upon that point; no doubt they might have had a kind return from the King, and ſuch a ſettlement of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as they could have deſired, and better than they now may expect. Therefore, ſince by your Confeſſion, ſo many never intended to anſwer the Kings <hi>Speech</hi> with more than a bare <hi>Complement;</hi> I do not think it was any ſuch difficulty, to <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain liberty of objecting againſt the Prerogative of Diſpenſing,</hi> which I ſuppoſe a great many more are now ſatisfied in the legality of, and when there is occaſion, both the Judges, and other Members of the long Robe, will make clear by Law and Equity.</p>
                  <p n="u">
                     <hi>(u)</hi> Sure there are numerous parties of all perſuaſions, who know how to ſet a right value on the <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government; but I will never reckon theſe in the number, who are for ſuch a ſtipulatory mixt Monarchy, as our old Publicans aſſerted; who at firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plementing the people, that the Original of the Supream Authority was in them, as ſoon as they had power, aſſumed it to themſelves, under the notion of Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation. To proceed, the end of the Journey will never be reached, if the Traveller ſet down his reſt in the midway. The King hath been the great <hi>Means</hi> and Author of this Liberty, and I hope it's not that time of the day to Vote Him <hi>dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</hi>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:100804:15"/>The way to have that preſerved, which is granted by the King, is to ſtudy by all thankfulneſs to preſerve His Royal Favour, and to preſs forward to obtain its compleat Eſtabliſhment, and never to ſound a <hi>Retreat,</hi> till they obtain the full enjoyment of the <hi>Praemium</hi> held out to them; which, if by flagging in the purſuit, they ſhall only enjoy during His Majeſties Life, they will have cauſe to repent <hi>at His Death,</hi> that they got it not better ſecured.</p>
                  <p n="x">
                     <hi>(x)</hi> Thanks for the <hi>Indulgence,</hi> and ſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous deſires to have it Parliamentarily Confirm'd, is taking <hi>time</hi> by the fore-top, and ſtriking while the Iron is hot. The Temple of <hi>Janus</hi> was opened in <hi>Auguſtus Caeſars</hi> time, as a certain ſign that the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire was then at peace: Should not Diſſenters rejoyce, even to ſome exceſs, that our <hi>Augustus</hi> hath now open'd it; whereby, through our <hi>Vito,</hi> they may ſee what Inteſtine jars, what effuſion of blood, the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> have made; and from the other may have the moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful Proſpect of large, and long laſting Freedom. By the Inſtances you bring of the Non-Conformiſts <hi>rough uſage</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> when they had the fleecing of it, and the manner of its retaliation. I ſhould think you ought to have determined the uſefulneſs, and neceſſity of embracing the Kings favour, whereby, neither party might Tyranize over the other for the future; rather then to decoy the Diſſenter, by the ſoft word of <hi>miſtake,</hi> as if either Party did ſuch miſchief to other, by ſome Venial Inadvertency only, when all the World knows, that the endeavours to ſecure their ſeveral Governments, occaſion'd the ſad galling of one another: Yet of the two, it is Demonſtrable, that the State Church of <hi>England</hi> Men were the favourableſt.</p>
                  <p n="y">
                     <hi>(y)</hi> Here you think to put the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters upon a <hi>Dilemma,</hi> that if they <hi>blame</hi>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:100804:16"/>the ſevere uſage of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> againſt them, they muſt not now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn it by being <hi>angry</hi> with them; or if they allow it they muſt not be <hi>offended</hi> at what they did. What if Diſſenters ſhall reply, that by too ſad experience they have found, that Perſecution was ruinous to both, and that it is neither <hi>Anger</hi> or <hi>Revenge</hi> againſt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that makes them ſo thankful to the King, and ſo deſirous that all Tuſhes may be filed off, whereby there may be no Tearing or Tyrannizing by any Party for Conſcience; but for eaſe-ſake, theſe have reaſon to wiſh the Rod burnt that felt the laſt ſmart of it; will not this Anſwer cut of the horned Argument?</p>
                  <p n="z">
                     <hi>(z)</hi> A Man not well skilled in your cunning, would judge you were owning all this, when you diſallow the Methods of the former <hi>Rigid Prelates,</hi> and would make Diſſenters believe, that the preſent Biſhops and Clergy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by the Senſe of their former <hi>miſtaken</hi> Rules, were content to lower their <hi>haughtineſs,</hi> and were ready to change the ſpirit of <hi>Perſecution and bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> for that of <hi>Charity and Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> But the Inference you make is very contrary and falacious; <hi>viz.</hi> that becauſe (if they believe you) the preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductors of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> are of an Uniting Temper; therefore the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters muſt ſo far relie upon their good na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that they muſt reject the offers of a moſt Gracious King, who endeavours to ſecure them from preſent and future ſufferings, and put it out of all peoples power, when the next favourable revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation comes, to have recourſe to former ſevereties. Suppoſe the Diſſenters ſay, that they may be juſtly jealous, that if a thouſand of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in this juncture, gave them an aſſurance
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100804:16"/>under their Hands and Seals, that they ſhould never be compelled under a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant King, to Conformity, they durſt not relie upon it, much leſs on ſuch a ſingle Voucher as your ſelf; what have you hitherto produced, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince ſuch unbelievers.</p>
                  <p n="a">
                     <hi>(a)</hi> Church-men, of all Societies, may be ſubject to like paſſions as other men, and I believe them not only <hi>humbleſt,</hi> but the charitableſt, beſt natured, and holyeſt too, when their <hi>power</hi> is not overgrown. But it doth not therefore follow, that the objecting the ſeverity of the Church of <hi>England</hi> againſt Diſſenters, when che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed by a Prince of her Communion, is <hi>uncharitable</hi> and <hi>ungenerous,</hi> much leſs, that it is <hi>miſ-timed:</hi> For if the Members of that Church did not endeavour to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Repeal of thoſe Laws, which only enable them to re-aſſume their Rods and Axes; Diſſenters might hope their kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was to be relied upon. But ſince they ſee them ſo unwilling to part with their offenſive Arms; even at the deſire of their Sovereign, they have juſt reaſon to think they ſcandalize them not, in ſaying, they dare not as yet believe that they intend them any good ſecurity that they will not call them to an after-reckoning, or that they will afford them ſuch an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of freedom, as they may now have under the Kings broad Seal. But to paſs on; I wonder not ſo much at your denying the Church of <hi>England</hi> is <hi>never humble but when ſhe wants power,</hi> for you may mean an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Church than other Mortals do; or by <hi>humble,</hi> you may mean ſhe leaſt uſeth Church Cenſures, when the Magiſtrates Inflict the Laws moſt <hi>ſeverely;</hi> which Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion you may, when preſſed, flie to. But the reaſon you give for it is more ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100804:17"/>that ſhe is even now meek and lowly, when ſhe hath power to confound all Diſſenters with a <hi>Breath.</hi> This indeed is a brisk flouriſh; like a brave Leaders encouragement to his ſeemingly foyled Party; that he hath one ſtratagem yet, which will gain the abſolute Victory, if they will credit his Conduct. I pray <hi>Sir,</hi> for all this rattle in the <hi>Clouds,</hi> (which is no more formidable than intelligible) give me leave to ask you, what this <hi>Smile,</hi> this <hi>kind Word,</hi> this <hi>glimps</hi> of <hi>Compliance,</hi> ſhould be, that can work ſuch wonders. There was a time, at, or before ſome Men were put to the <hi>Test,</hi> when a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with the Kings deſires of Repeal, would have continued ſeveral Eminent Men in their Stations, and they would have felt many effects of His Majeſties Royal Favour. But all <hi>that</hi> would have been as a reward of their publick ſplritedneſs, and concurrence with the King, in the truly <hi>Catholick</hi> deſign of making all His Subjects eaſie as to their Religious Concerns. But it looks like Preſumption, yea, inſolence in you, to aſſert, that when ſuch have loſt the opportunity of preſerving themſelves in the Kings good Opinion, He ſhould take them into His Throne, and permit them to guide His Arm, to dart His <hi>Thunder</hi> where they pleaſe. No, if they ſhould offer all compliance, for the future ſecuring <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> provided they might execute <hi>Penal Laws</hi> againſt Diſſenters, yet this would have no power to encline a Prince, ſo ſteady to His Reſolutions, and the publick Declaration of His Judgement, to alter in the leaſt His Royal purpoſe, of granting Univerſal <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> to ſuch as would live peaceably, and give no diſturbance to the Civil Government. Much leſs can thoſe hope to prevail, who declare all <hi>Compliance</hi> with the Kings deſires ſo <hi>Criminal</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſtifiable,</hi> that they will rather chooſe to ſtand mute, and be preſs'd to Death, in hopes to preſerve their Eſtates for the next Heir, then to quit their beloved <hi>Teſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="b">
                     <hi>(b)</hi> As to <hi>Provocation,</hi> while you write, you commit the fault you ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely complain of. As to thoſe Books, writ upon the ſubject of Religion; every one may obſerve, that thoſe, in defence of the Proteſtant Doctrine, have been
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100804:17"/>throngly cryed about the ſtreets, with the Emphaſis of being Vindications of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the Licenſes of the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> or Biſhop of <hi>London;</hi> whereas, <hi>Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick</hi> Books, except ſome few Sermons of the Fathers, have been diſpers'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the pomp of a publick Cryer. Only ſome Diſſenters, concern'd to give pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Teſtimonies of their gratitude to the King, have enlarged the Gazets, and ſet ſome Printing Preſſes on work. But that any ſuch Writers are <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakers,</hi> or have made any Contracts with the <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> to begin a <hi>Fray</hi> among <hi>Proteſtants for the ſport or advantage</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> I ſee no ſhadow of Reaſon. Since the Intereſt they have to own the eaſe they find by His Majeſties <hi>Indulgence,</hi> and the Oppoſition they find from ſome Members of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to it, are ſufficient Motives to them to write and ſpeak all they have hitherto done. And your entring the Liſts with ſo many fine devices on your Helm and Shield, and all over your whole Armour, cannot but Excite many Combitants to engage ſo gaudy a Challenger.</p>
                  <p n="c">
                     <hi>(c)</hi> What you expect to be <hi>applauded</hi> or <hi>commended</hi> in this <hi>conduct,</hi> I cannot tell! Perſecution for Conſcience you own to be ill, yet you would not have it <hi>equal dealing</hi> to <hi>blame</hi> ſuch who op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Repeal of ſuch Laws, as only arm Perſecutors, which is dancing in a Circle.</p>
                  <p n="d">
                     <hi>(d)</hi> To hate the cauſers of our Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, is very natural in thoſe, who have not learnt to pray for their Enemies; but for the <hi>Perſecuted</hi> to court and love the Perſecutors, who judge it Criminal, and are <hi>ready to ſuffer</hi> themſelves, rather than yield up the wheels, racks, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100804:18"/>ſtrapado's, fetters and chains, and the cruel inſtruments of Perſecution, when the Supream Magiſtrate forbids it, is a <hi>Principle,</hi> neither <hi>Heathen</hi> or <hi>Chriſtian can own:</hi> So that I will not trouble my head to Divine what the <hi>Objection</hi> ſhould be that you acquaint us not with, and yet you ſay is <hi>un-anſwerable.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="e">
                     <hi>(e)</hi> I have heard it accounted as ſome ſolace, to have Companions in miſery; but never that any took delight in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing Torments to others, that they might have more ſtripes themſelves. How the Papiſts ſhould promote the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> againſt Diſſenters, is a Ridle: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, it is not dutifully done, to make the Church of <hi>England</hi> the Lictors and Bedels of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> but ſome will loſe their Friend, e're they loſe their Jeſt, or falſe Sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion.</p>
                  <p n="f">
                     <hi>(f)</hi> This Paragraph ought to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted for at <hi>Weſtminster-Hall.</hi> Before there can be any ſenſe made of it; it muſt be moſt ſcandalouſly ſuppos'd, that the King is about to alter the <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of the <hi>Election</hi> of <hi>Knights</hi> and <hi>Burgeſſes,</hi> and to deſign another, <hi>Praiſe God Barebone</hi> Parliament; then which, no reflection can be more odious.</p>
                  <p n="g">
                     <hi>(g)</hi> When-ever the Diſpenſing Power is argu'd, I doubt not but many more Members in Parliament will allow it, than did before the point had been ſo cleared as now; and in duty we ought to believe the King, by the Repeal, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends no more than what He expreſſes in His Royal Declaration, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the <hi>Indulgence</hi> to ſecure the Church of <hi>England</hi> in her rights and poſſeſſion of the Honours and Revenues, and Liberty both to it and Diſſenters; which being done, there will be no room for thoſe unreaſonable Surmiſes.</p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:100804:18"/>
                  <p n="h">
                     <hi>(h)</hi> The great <hi>Talbots</hi> Name was long after his Death us'd to affright the Children of <hi>France</hi> with. Is it fit that a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Gentleman ſhould judge all Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſuch Children, as to be affrighted with the Name of <hi>Roman Conſiſtory.</hi> Our Lawful Sovereign is the only <hi>Lord of the Articles,</hi> who will propoſe the Queſtion, and Obedience in this caſe may be more beneficial, than to be always made Sacrifices by ſevere <hi>Penal Laws.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="i">
                     <hi>(i)</hi> Is it a <hi>Parliament</hi> of two Houſes you mean, ſhall offer this <hi>Indulgence</hi> to Diſſenters? or would you have them ſtay to the next Ages? If the firſt, you deſerve the doom of a Traitor, ſince you muſt Exclude the King, unleſs <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> be included; if the latter, you muſt fit the Diſſenters with Iron Shooes.</p>
                  <p n="k">
                     <hi>(k)</hi> You Write as if you were one of the Plenipotentiaries at a <hi>Treaty</hi> betwixt <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> and Diſſenters, and were well acquainted with the ſecret <hi>Articles.</hi> All the World hath judged Diſſenters to have a great averſion to implicit Faith and blind Obedience; but they muſt all be the moſt abſolute Reſigners of their Reaſon and Religion, to the guidance of <hi>Roman Catholicks:</hi> If for this pretended Liberty of Conſcience, as you call it, they muſt Sacrifice their real Freedom. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve rather that the weight and galling of their late Chains, are ſo much felt, that they will be very unwilling to have them put on again by ſome Members of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and the confidence to be ever freed from them, makes them ſo ready to embrace this Jayl-Delivery.</p>
                  <p n="l">
                     <hi>(l)</hi> To what degree ſoever either <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> or Diſſenters may judge valid the <hi>Diſpenſing Power;</hi> yet, that no ways ſhould hinder them, from deſiring the <hi>Indulgence</hi> may be Eſtabliſhed by Law, to perpetuate that favour which they, at
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:100804:19"/>preſent, are only ſecure of during the Kings Life: And as all Gracious and juſt Princes, deſire their Honour and good Fame may long out-live them; ſo they wiſh, that the benefits they intend for their people, may be extended to future Ages. Therefore, however His Majeſty may be ſatisfied in the rights of His So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereignty, yet for the tender regard of the future Repoſe of His Subjects: It is a moſt Gracious Act in Him, to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the concurrence of His Two Houſes, which by an impropriety of Speech you call the <hi>Legiſlative;</hi> when it is well known, that without the Royal concurrence, the Two Houſes are only the <hi>Legiſpreparative.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="m">
                     <hi>(m)</hi> By thoſe words, <hi>and not without Reaſon,</hi> you diſcover your ſelf to have been a Secluſioniſt; and yet want the candor of an ingenuous Diſſenter, who is not angry that thoſe Members of the Church of <hi>England complied</hi> ſo far; ſince it hath given them the opportunity of experiencing the Kings ſurprizing Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, and condemning the groundleſs jealouſie they had of Him, which prompted to that Reluctancy againſt His Rightful Succeſſion; and the Diſſenters have no reaſon to be ſorry, that theſe Members of the Church of <hi>England</hi> made no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Progreſs after the King came to the Crown. Since that <hi>ſtop</hi> of theirs made the Wheel move faſter towards the <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,</hi> the benefit whereof leaſt they ſhould be in danger to loſe, they will with all ſedulity endeavour to promote, though I preſume, by no indirect means, but ſuch as may be agreeable to the duty of their Allegiance and Thankfulneſs, they owe to the King for it. Then the ſcrupulous niceneſs concerning ſignificant Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:100804:19"/>will ceaſe, becauſe none will be obliged to uſe the Cope, Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice, or long Cloak, but ſuch as like them; only I hope it will be always prohibited to Preach in Buff-coats, and mingle Blood with their Oblations.</p>
                  <p n="n">
                     <hi>(n)</hi> Nothing is more common, than to find Names affixed according to peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples fancies, and after a while one word ſerves for Deſcription, Definition, and Character. If <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> once be made practicable, and in the vogue, Thoſe diſcriminating Cyphers will be uſeleſs, and all Subjects will be conſidered in their morality, or immorality, obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, or diſobedience, rather than by the Cognizance of their Religion: It is no ſtrange thing in Nature, that by ſome influence of the Heavens, and aptneſs of Soyl, ſome Plants may <hi>ſhoot</hi> up more in a Night than others, backned by ſevere Froſts, do in a Month; and why the rare Plant of <hi>Liberty</hi> in Religious Worſhip, may not be as perennial as the Thiſtle of Perſecution, I ſee no great Reaſon, if Cultivated with common care. If the proſpect of continual ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and the want of Chriſtian Liberty, made Diſſenters <hi>Factious and Rebellious;</hi> it is to be preſumed, that the Fundimental Inſtigation being removed, the Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft will no longer prevail. It is the concernment of all Governments, to ſee that Men be true to it e're they be truſted; and when Princes lay by their co-active Laws, it is the intereſt of the Subjects to lay aſide their Animoſities, and when all Parties quit their Fire-Arms, and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Weapons, I ſee no reaſon to deſpair of Harmony and Accord in the duty of Chriſtians and Subjects; and thus being <hi>linked in</hi> the common bond of freedom, I ſee no occaſion to throw one another <hi>off again.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:100804:20"/>
                  <p n="o">
                     <hi>(o)</hi> If things now tend <hi>naturally</hi> to the <hi>eaſe</hi> of Diſſenters, they have reaſon to be moſt thankful to the King, as the ſole beſtower of it; and I ſee no Reaſon they ſhould let go the Bird in hand, in hopes to catch another in the Buſh. I ſhould think they acted with leſs circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection than they have wonted to do; if they ſlip the opportunity of that ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der made them, in expectation of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying any thing like it, when the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſhall be in a flouriſhing condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Beſides, it may be a Queſtion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Toleration after the patern of the Low Countries, may not be more preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> than ſuch one as may be now adjuſted.</p>
                  <p n="p">
                     <hi>(p)</hi> Here you are very Magiſterial, and have undertaken far more than your Credit will go for. To ſay a Church is convinced of an Errour, befits none but the Prolocutor of a Convocation, when ſuch a Vote was paſſed with a <hi>Nemine Contradicente,</hi> and to enſure for a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Votes, is more than any Ten Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of it can do. But I preſume you ſpeak by Figure here, that if Diſſenters will not joyn with <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> to be thankful for the <hi>Indulgence,</hi> and will ſtick cloſe to the Members of the Church of <hi>England</hi> that oppoſe it; then the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament under a <hi>Protestant</hi> Succeſſor, and a Convocation will ſet ſuch a value upon that ſervice, that they will be gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile to them, and eſtabliſh ſome Bill of comprehenſion, which the Governours of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> could never hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto be brought to yield to. All this looks ſo like decoy, that the Diſſenter of the loweſt form will perceive it. But what ever they do, all thinking Men, muſt judge the deſign of this is to animate all Proteſtants to weather out the point, and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100804:20"/>heighten their oppoſition to the King, which in former times would have been ſtil'd Sedition. As to that excellent Princeſs, I ſuppoſe you mean, few Princeſſes in <hi>Europe</hi> are known to Excell Her in the Accompliſhments of Body or Mind; and as Her Royal Father is as Indulgent to Her Highneſs, as any Prince can be; ſo She is as Dutiful; and whatever the King Eſtabliſheth in His time for the publick Good and Tranquility of His Kingdoms, if She over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live Him, I preſume it may be Her deſire, if not Her Intereſt to <hi>ratifie;</hi> and to what perfection ſoever His Majeſty may bring this Pantheon, there may ſtill remain beautifying, and adorning for His Succeſſor, and room enough to enlarge the <hi>Foundations,</hi> and build ſtronger Defences againſt the <hi>common</hi> Enemy of Perſecution, if this conſpiring againſt a work, which You own Diſſenters need, and deſerve, do not <hi>deſtroy</hi> it.</p>
                  <p n="q">
                     <hi>(q)</hi> In this Paragraph you are numbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the people, and examining Your ſtrength by the Muſter-roll; and the head of thoſe Powers you deſign to Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, is manifeſtly the King, which is not very agreeable to the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> Doctrine of <hi>Non-Reſiſtance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="r">
                     <hi>(r)</hi> Good words butter no Parſnips; if the Expreſſions of Duty were not tainted and hollow, and in your Opinion His Majeſties Religion did not only ſhade, but totally Eclipſe His Vertues: Your Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance would not look, as it doth, more like a Submiſſion than a Duty; nor would You adventure upon that Bravado, that ſome own their beſt ſecurity to Paſſive Obedience, and the Doctrine of <hi>Non-Reſiſtance,</hi> which look very like bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> beware leaſt they rouſe a ſleeping Lyon: For I know not who they are that Laugh at the commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Doctrine of <hi>Non-Reſiſtance;</hi> but when I ſee Men fomenting jealouſies againſt their Sovereign, ridiculing His Conduct, endeavouring to Repreſent Him as acting againſt the Laws, aſſuming an Arbitrary Power, denying Him the ſervice of all His Subjects, and by all poſſible Arts, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to withdraw the Affections of the people from Him ſolely,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:100804:21"/>becauſe of His Religion; I cannot judge ſuch to be true practicers of that Doctrine.</p>
                  <p n="ſ">
                     <hi>(ſ)</hi> Here you give a touch of your Aſtrology, and it being cuſtomary for the pretenders to that Art, to attempt by Horary Queſtions to know Diſeaſes, and after a while to ſet up for Empericks: So you give us a pretty Receipt to clear a lowring Sky; the Senſe of which is, for all Proteſtants to lye in of the ſullen, keep their beds, and there uſe ſome kind of reaſonable Devotion, and entertain their Viſitants with diſcourſes of their Loyalty, and their adhering to the Laws, and it will be twenty to one but they will be freed from the Hail-ſtorm, and eſcape the danger of the Infectious Air. But leſt any ſhould object that, <hi>Bed-zid</hi> Proteſtants are not like to keep out <hi>Popery,</hi> you have a moſt Infallible <hi>Elixir</hi> in your Repoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, which is, that neither the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Diſſenters ought to be affrighted with any fear that the <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Religion can be Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by a Toleration (ſince the ods is two hundred to one) without a greater <hi>Miracle</hi> than any we read of in any <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gend,</hi> eſpecially in the <hi>old Age</hi> of a Church, which hath been <hi>ſo long barren</hi> of them. For ſhame therefore give over your falſe Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rums; amuſe the Diſſenters no more to ſuch circumſpect ſtanding upon their guard, to keep out <hi>Popery,</hi> ſince in our days there is no feeding Five hundred with <hi>Five Loves and two Fiſhes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="t">
                     <hi>(t)</hi> The concluſion is agreeable to your <hi>premiſes,</hi> an Exhortation to an Aſſociation a gainſt the King, and all of His judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the matters of the <hi>Teſt;</hi> and the motives to it are pretty odd, that ſince both Parties have been too blame, in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting one another, therefore they ſhould be reconciled, and combine in oppoſing the <hi>Indulgence,</hi> which is moſt
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:100804:21"/>likely to put an end to all rancor and malice. One would have thought, that the Inference more naturally ſhould have been, that ſince they both had experienced the miſchiefs of Perſecution, and neither of them bettered their condition by it, therefore, they ſhould both have joyned in the promoting the general <hi>Indulgence,</hi> that there might be no more ſtrife among them, ſince they were Brethren; I am ſure this had more truly reſolved the Queſtion. But inſtead of this, you tell the Diſſenters, (without giving any Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for it) that diſ-union is not only a <hi>Reproach,</hi> but a <hi>danger</hi> to both. This I own to be true, if the Union you deſire were for the publick good of both, but if the Union be to combine you and them in equal undutifulneſs and ingratefulneſs to the King; if this Union be deſired to hinder the Kings Progreſs in His laudable purpoſes; if this Union be but to while the buſineſs with a <hi>Shall I, Shall I,</hi> to tire the Kings Patience, and diſappoint His expectation, it will redound to both the Diſſenters and your <hi>Danger,</hi> if not <hi>Reproach.</hi> To perſuade to ſuch an Union as this, is the whole drift of your diſcourſe, and ſomething you muſt mean more than Paſſive Obedience, when you rivet the Nail you have all this while been driving in, telling your <hi>Reader,</hi> that it is as <hi>unjuſtifiable to have no Religion, as wilfully to throw away the means of preſerving it.</hi> This looks like a ſecond ſound to Horſe; and you have a pretty ſlight in your Mouth, to perſuade <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> (becauſe you think them ſo credulous of Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles) to neglect all <hi>Cautions</hi> or means to preſerve themſelves, but to relie upon a Supernatural Power: But thoſe of your Principles muſt uſe the <hi>Humane Means</hi> of preſerving it, and of how many Battalions theſe muſt conſiſt, though you have reaſon to conceal the Intimation from the World; yet you give a ſufficient <hi>Item,</hi> what may be expected, and thereby <hi>caution</hi> the Government to have more Circumſpection over your Sayings and Actions.</p>
                  <p>Thus <hi>Sir,</hi> I have now finiſhed my Obſervations upon your <hi>Letter;</hi> I ſhall ſubjoyn ſomething the ſubject matter induceth me to offer to the conſideration of all Chriſtian Dutiful Subjects, and then cloſe the whole.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="excursus">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:100804:22"/>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I have hitherto follow'd the train you have lead me, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to give a reaſonable Anſwer to the moſt material parts of your <hi>Letter.</hi> What was bare ſuppoſal, and groundleſs ſuſpicion I have not much concerned my ſelf with. Thoſe being but like the Feathering of unpiled Arrows, which help their flight, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force them little to do harm, where-ever they fall. Neither have I attempted to reach the Towring Flights of your Oratory, which how Ornimental ſoever, are but like mounting Bubbles, which break and vaniſh when at the utmoſt ſtretch. Your affrightments, when well conſidered, are but like the ſparks in a Smiths-ſhop, which upon a brisk heat and ſtroak, fills all with ſeeming liquid fire, yet it is as ſoon extinguiſhed as the Iron cools, or the labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtroke ceaſeth. What was Seditious, and tending to inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate the Subjects to jealouſies and diſloyal Opinions of their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign, I have endeavoured to Diſprove, and Repreſs. What was Calumny, I have gently wiped off; unleſs when it was couched in ſuch general Terms, as placed it beyond all reach of the Spung. Rebells in open Hoſtility, are not ſo dangerous to a Prince, and His Governmet, though the ſevereſt Puniſhments are inflicted on them when maſtered; as thoſe are, who by ſly Arts, Detraction, evil Surmiſes and Conſtructions, render their Prince ſuſpected of Ruling Arbitrarily, and altering Religion and Laws; and thereby blaſt His Credit with His people: For thoſe are the Men that make the whole Reigns of Princes troubleſom, and unfortunate to Themſelves and their Subjects. Theſe Liſt the Men, provide Magazines and Arms, and prepare all things in readineſs againſt the ſound of the Trumpet, and do not only Muſter the Rebels, but they do, as much as in them lyes, to enfeeble or taint the Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the remainder.</p>
               <p>You have contributed all you poſſibly can to effect theſe things, and expoſed your <hi>Letter</hi> as a Banner to invite to jealouſies and fears, which are the very <hi>Avant-couriers</hi> of Sedition and Rebellion; and this in you that pretend to be a Son of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is ſo much the worſe, in that you know how ſtrictly it enjoyns Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Lawful Sovereign, and how much the Doctrine of <hi>Non-Reſiſtance</hi> hath been taught and practiſed by its Members.</p>
               <p>If the Kings Intentions to ſettle the <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Religion by force, (which you ſurely cannot in good earneſt believe practica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) were much more apparent than it is: If the inevitable ruine of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> here, ſhould be the conſequence of the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:100804:22"/>
                  <hi>Repeal;</hi> and if the exerciſe of His Prerogative and Diſpenſing Power, were the certain ruine of all Mens Properties, you and others who own no other Loyalty to their Sovereign, than what is conſiſtent with their ſuppoſed Intereſt, could not invent more provoking Reflections upon the King, or miſ-interpret His Actions worſe than you do.</p>
               <p>But how unreaſonably undutiful is it in Subjects, and thoſe who would be reputed the zealouſeſt for our Church, to charge the King with Intrigue and Hypocriſy, or breach of promiſe; who of all Princes living deteſts mear tricks, and to prevaricate with any: To whom Diſſimulation is the odiouſeſt of Vices, and whoſe very In-bred, Natural, and Heroick courage, places Him as much above all low Arts, as His Dignity doth above His Subjects.</p>
               <p>Beſides all the un-anſwerable Arguments which have been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, why the taking off the <hi>Teſt</hi> and <hi>Penal Laws</hi> cannot work ſuch a change in our Religion; you may conſider, that at the ſame time the Church of <hi>England</hi> may be Inſured by Laws of greateſt caution. Furthermore we have moſt ſolemn and publick promiſes, <hi>That His Majeſty will Protect and Maintain the Church of</hi> England <hi>in the free exerciſe of its Religion, as by Law Eſtabliſhed, and in the quiet and full enjoyment of all Her Poſſeſſions, without any moleſtation or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbance,</hi> which He will inviolably obſerve; If by a ſtubborneſs, that ſhall be unpardonable in the judgement of all Impartial Men, we forfeit not a Clemency ſo rarely to be parallel'd. To all which may be added, the univerſal averſion of the Nobility, Gentry, and Commonality to the <hi>Roman Catholick Religion,</hi> occaſioned even by the deepeſt Impreſſion that Education, Cuſtom, and an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Purity, and Primativeneſs of it, hath made.</p>
               <p>If none of theſe Arguments will prevail with you to change your evil Opinion of the Kings deſigns by the <hi>Repeal;</hi> conſider delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, I pray you, how the King muſt overthrow the very Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation upon which the great Enterprize of Univerſal Liberty, and conſequently of all the Benefits to His people, by enriching them, and keeping them in peace, and ſecuring the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> in future times in any tollerable ſtate, if He ever give way to inveſt any one Church-Community with a Coercive Power.</p>
               <p>But I know it is Objected, that if a Toleration only were inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, how comes it to paſs, that ſo many Loyal Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> even of thoſe who ſo couragiouſly adhered to the Crown in its utmoſt danger, are now diſplaced, and the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> or Diſſenters, even ſuch of the laſt, as have moſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently oppoſed His Majeſties Succeſſion, are ſubſtituted in their Rooms?</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:100804:23"/>
               <p>In anſwer to this, It is well known, that the number of <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> Employed by the King in His Court, in His Council, in His Courts of <hi>Judicature,</hi> in Camp, and all Places of publick Employments, almoſt as far exceed the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> as our Clergy do theirs; and yet we make ſo hideous a noiſe at the Conferring Places and Honours upon ſome deſerving and Loyal <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> and two or three Maſters, and a few Fellows of Colleges being Preferr'd; which are but the effects of common diſtributive Juſtice, and conſentaneous to the Paternal care of ſuch a Prince, who would ſhow ſome marks of favour to thoſe few of His own Religion, who are not now ſurely to be wholly Excluded. Therefore, in my judgement, it ſhows a very ill Nature in thoſe who own His Majeſty to be their Lawful King, and that He may at His Pleaſure uſe the ſervice of which of His Subjects He pleaſes, to grudge His intermixing ſo few of His own Religion with others.</p>
               <p>Beſides this, you cannot be ignorant, that it never was the practice of any Prince, or Government, what Religion ſoever, to imploy Subjects in Places of Truſt, who ſet themſelves directly to oppoſe, what by prudent forecaſt for the publick good, they determined to Eſtabliſh. Now ſince the King, for the Reaſons publiſhed in His <hi>Gracious Declaration,</hi> is ſo intent upon compleating this great work of General Freedom, and ſecuring thoſe of His own Religion, in common with the reſt. It cannot be thought reaſonable, or expedient, that He ſhould cheriſh and countenance thoſe, who ſo bitterly oppoſe him in it: Eſpecially ſince it is ſo apparent, that even ſuch, who have ſhown great zeal for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the Crown upon the Heads of their Proteſtant Sovereigns, now manifeſt, not only an indifference, and coldneſs, but an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becoming way wardneſs to the Kings Service: In ſo much, that ſome decline ſitting in Commiſſion with <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Juſtices of the Peace, and others think it honourable to quit their places, rather than to make one ſtep towards the <hi>Repeal;</hi> ſo that even the Badges and Livery of Loyalty are changed, from that to the King, to that of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and thoſe who make the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt complaint of hard uſage, have themſelves turned the Tables.</p>
               <p>As to Diſſenters, it is their Intereſt to cloſe with the Crown ſide for Protection, and ſince they can derive this unlooked for favour from none but the King, they ſhould be the moſt ungrateful of Men, if with chearfulneſs, and ſincerity, they did not pay all poſſible Acknowledgments to His Majeſties Bounty for it. So that I do not wonder to hear them, with great Aſſeveration ſay, it was not for a <hi>Commonwealth</hi> they fought, and were continually ſtriving againſt
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:100804:23"/>the ſtream, but it was to get the Weather-gage of Perſecution: It was to obtain this <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> which they never could expect from former Governments, that provoked them to commit ſuch Hainous things they now are aſhamed of; and which, indeed they ought to Attone for in another manner than they have hitherto done. They now declare, that if they might have had the Tenth of that Liberty the Church of <hi>England</hi> now enjoys, under our Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious King, they would never have lifted up an hand, or opened a Mouth againſt the late Kings of bleſſed Memories, and I think they are the rather to be believed, becauſe neither the Doctrine, nor the Ceremonies of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> are ſo much declaim'd againſt by them now, as thoſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which they formerly reputed Idolatrous: They now think themſelves juſtified in their Eſpouſing the Parliaments ſide, from whom they expected, and had <hi>Indulgence,</hi> and pleaſe themſelves to find ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kind of <hi>non Addreſſors,</hi> and as zealous perſons to hinder the <hi>Repeal</hi> of <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> againſt their Sovereigns declared deſire, as they were formerly for it. Yet, though the Scene be thus changed, I hope there are ſufficient numbers of ſuch, whom the Church of <hi>England</hi> will own to be her Children, that will let no Diſſenters out-goe them in Loyalty, and Dutifulneſs to their Sovereign; and who are well aſſured, the King will have as great regard to them, and our Church for their ſakes; and as freely permit them the enjoyment of the Exerciſe of their Religion and Benefices, as to any, provided they will concur with Him in the <hi>Repeal,</hi> and be content to let their Fellow-Subjects, of different Perſuaſions, enjoy likewiſe their <hi>Liberty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the Members of the Church of <hi>England</hi> ought to yield this in common prudence, and even for the Preſervation of their own Religion, I think there are many Reaſons; eſpecially this, that as yet the time is not clapſed, but that when His Majeſty convenes His Parliament, ſufficient Security may be obtained, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſhall enjoy all the King hath promiſed; and when, by the Wiſdom of the Houſes, ſuch an Act is contrived, as will anſwer the Kings deſires of the Univerſal eaſe of His Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, the Church of <hi>England</hi> will feel as great effects of the Kings kindneſs, as ſhe can expect, or deſire; and by the freedom all will enjoy, there will be no more conteſts; but who ſhall <hi>approve</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves moſt dutiful and deſerving of His Majeſties Clemency, and Kindneſs. Upon ſuch a cloſure, the <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> and Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters will freely yield to the mutual ſecurity of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and that Church will regain its Reputation of Loyalty, and confirm what you promiſe in her name, of being kind to Diſſenters,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:100804:24"/>and a <hi>Proteſtant Prince</hi> ſucceeding, and finding things thus Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cably Compoſed, will reap the benefit, as the whole Kingdom will do, of this happy undertaking of the King.</p>
               <p>But on the contrary, if the Majority of the Members of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in Parliament, obſtinately <hi>oppoſe</hi> the Kings deſires, they will oblige His Majeſty to purſue other Methods, and it will give occaſion to all ſuch as are no great well-wiſhers to our Church, to urge its uncharitableneſs; that rather than it will permit the King to exerciſe His Prerogative, of being ſerved with all His Subjects, of what denomination ſoever He pleaſes to make uſe of, and that Men of different Profeſſions in Religion, may enjoy the favour of the Kings <hi>Indulgence,</hi> they will put themſelves out of His Royal Protection, and abſolve Him from His promiſe therein; and the upſhot of all will be, that by His Majeſties ſteady purſuit of this great work, which He firmly believes will conduce ſo much to the univerſal good of His Subjects; In a few years, by ſuch ſedulous countenancing all thoſe, who will ſtrenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly co-operate with Him to effect it, the Diſſenters will obtain the Majority of Voices in Parliament, which if once effected, thoſe Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who have Obſtructed the <hi>Repeal,</hi> will be at the mercy of Diſſenters; and if the King be not their beſt Friend, may fall ſhort of what they may now ſo effectually obtain.</p>
               <p>I ſhall conclude with a ſhort Paraphraſe upon the Words His Majeſty, uſed to His Privy Council <hi>March</hi> the 8th. 1686. concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this <hi>Indulgence,</hi> in which the ſubſtance of what need be ſaid, in juſtifying the Kings granting it, are clearly laid down.</p>
               <p>Firſt, His Majeſty ſhows the practice of former Ages, and the ſucceſs of them; That <hi>although an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity in the Religious Worſhip had been Endeavoured to be Eſtabliſhed within this Kingdom, in the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive Reigns of Four of His Majesties Royal Predeceſſors, aſſiſted by their reſpective Parliaments; yet it hath proved altogether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is obvious to every one that reads the Hiſtory of thoſe times, and well know to thoſe that lived in the beginning of the Rebellion; for Diſſenters were then ſo encreaſed, that they were numerous, and powerful enough to overthrow, not only the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but the Monarchy that defended it. The Kings Words are, <hi>That the Reſtraint upon the Conſciences of Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, in order thereunto, viz.</hi> to Conformity, <hi>had been very prejudicial to this Nation, as was ſadly experienced in the horrid Rebellion, in the time of His Majeſties Royal Father.</hi> The King then pitcheth upon the true and principal cauſe of all thoſe <hi>Calamities</hi> that befel the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:100804:24"/>bleſſed Martyr, and were freſhly commencing again in the later time of His Majeſties Royal Brothers Reign, which are beſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the Kings own Words, <hi>That the many</hi> Penal Laws <hi>made againſt Diſſenters, in all the foregoing Reigns, and eſpecially in the time of the late King, had rather increaſed than leſſened them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If therefore our Gracious King, out of an exceſs of love and Paternal care, did not ſtudy the Univerſal benefit, eaſe, profit, and enriching of His people, He might have purſued former Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedents: But as a Wiſe and Compaſſionate Prince, He ſearcheth diligently for the true Cauſes; and while too many are buſying themſelves in Traducing His zeal for His Religion, as if it were the only concern of His Royal Cares. He Demonſtrates to all His Subjects, how much more ſollicitous He is to find ſome better Method, whereby at once He may Eſtabliſh His Throne, and thoſe of His Succeſſors, in a ſtable peace and ſecurity, and give Eaſe, Freedom, and Riches, to all His People, of what Perſuaſtion ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever: Therefore declares, <hi>That nothing can more conduce to the peace and quiet of His Kingdom, and the increaſe of the Numbers, as well as the Trade of the Subjects, (wherein the greatneſs of a Prince does more conſiſt, than in the extent of His Teritories) than an entire Liberty of Conſcience.</hi> That His Majeſty may likewiſe obviate all the great ſcruple ſuch as you raiſe as if He did this for any private ends; you have His Royal Word to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, when He tells all His Subjects, <hi>That it hath been His Opinion, as moſt ſuitable to the Principles of Chriſtianity, that no Man ſhould be Perſecuted for Conſcience ſake, which His Majeſty thinks is not to be forced.</hi> By this His Majeſty ſhows, that He grounds not His judgement upon the agreeableneſs, or ungreeableneſs of it to the intereſt of any Church; but as it is ſuitable to the uery Principles of Chriſtian Religion, and having by this ſhown His Royal Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions how to proceed upon that bottom, during His own Reign, out of a well grounded Confidence, that it may be a rule and ſtandard to His Royal Succeſſors, He cloſeth all with this Maxim, <hi>That it can never be the true Intereſt of a King of</hi> England, <hi>to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to force Conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Have not all Men from hence, and all His Majeſties Actions, reaſon to think, there is a Clemency, Benignity, and tenderneſs in the King to His Subjects, flowing in His Princely Blood from His Royal Anceſtors, and peculiar to the family, which His Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion can never alter; ſo that where the neceſſity of His people, rather han His own ſafety, does not oblige Him to ſeverity, We ſee daily inſtances of a Mercifulneſs beyond all expectation, and even to the envy of others, ſome of which have been very
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:100804:25"/>late: and if this difficulty of the <hi>Repeal</hi> were once over, all His Subjects would know, that He would deſerve the <hi>Epethites</hi> of Juſt, Merciful, and Pacifick, as well as any of His Royal Predeceſſors; having that perſonal Courage, and Fortitude, over and above what is to be found in few Crowned Heads; ſo that <hi>ſatis eſt proſtraſſe,</hi> muſt be owned by all His Majeſties ill-willers, as pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to His Generoſity.</p>
               <p>I ſhould here have cloſed this Diſcourſe, but that I find His Majeſties late <hi>Speech</hi> to the LORD MAYOR and <hi>Aldermen</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> when they Preſented Him with their late <hi>Addreſs,</hi> hath occaſioned a new Miſrepreſentation; becauſe His Majeſty mentioned the advantages would redound to the Subjects by a general <hi>Naturalization</hi> and publick <hi>Regiſter,</hi> which thoſe who ſuck poiſon out of every flower, cenſure as manifeſt tokens, that if theſe be effected, the growth of Popery will be promoted, which they thus prove.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> that <hi>Naturilization</hi> will open a door, to let in from foreign parts, ſuch ſholes of <hi>Roman Catholicks,</hi> that the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſhall ſoon be out-numbered. <hi>Secondly,</hi> that a publick Regiſter will ſo diſcover all Mens Eſtates, that the King may eaſily diſpoſe of them, when the Laws of <hi>Property</hi> ſhall be, as now we ſee <hi>Penal Laws</hi> are diſpenſed with.</p>
               <p>As to the firſt of theſe malicious Inſinuations, I deſire all think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Men to conſider, that it is a very known Maxim, that not only the power of any Prince, but the Riches of every Kingdom con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in the multitude of the people well Governed. Let us now therefore conſider who they are, that are likelieſt to flock hither, if an Act of general <hi>Naturilization</hi> ſhould paſs. There are none that leave their own Country, to Tranſplant themſelves into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Soil, but ſuch as have a Proſpect to live more at eaſe abroad, than in their own Country, and ſuch muſt be principally thoſe, who retire to avoid Perſecution for their Religion, or are obnoxious to the Laws, for ſome notorious Treſpaſſes againſt them, or ſuch who dare not ſhow their Heads for Debt; or laſtly, thoſe who in the way of Traffick think to better their Fortunes. For it is ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to imagine, that <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Princes will unpeople their Countries, to ſend Colonies abroad, unleſs it were to make War; and to ſuch, I preſume, no Law of <hi>Naturilization</hi> will extend.</p>
               <p>I ſuppoſe then, no Objections will be made to the incoming of <hi>Aliens,</hi> but ſuch as do it upon a Religious account. Let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſider, who they are that can flock hither, becauſe they want the freedom of their Religion in their own Countries? and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:100804:25"/>ſurely in <hi>Europe</hi> we can find none, except they are <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> that are in ſuch a ſtate under <hi>Catholick Princes;</hi> and it will be very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to believe, they will fly Perſecution at home, to turn <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> here.</p>
               <p>Therefore it appears moſt manifeſt, that the only effect ſuch a Law can have, will be to bring from <hi>Poland,</hi> ſome parts of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many, Denmark, Sweden,</hi> or <hi>Holland,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Refugees, ſince <hi>England</hi> is known to be a place of more comfortable Retreat than thoſe Countries are; and if ſuch <hi>French,</hi> or any other <hi>Aliens,</hi> were Diſperſed, in ſome proportion, through the Kingdom, and not ſuffered all to ſettle in the Populous City of <hi>London;</hi> there might be hopes, that by their Induſtry, and Trades, as well as the conſumption of the growth of the Country, there would be advantage to the Kingdom by their numbers.</p>
               <p>Thus I hope I have made it appear, how directly contrary an effect, to what is ſuggeſted, would naturally follow upon a Bill of <hi>Naturalization, viz.</hi> the increaſe of <hi>Protestants,</hi> if of any.</p>
               <p>As to the publick <hi>Regiſter,</hi> it is notoriouſly known, how attempts have been made in former Ages to have effected this, and it is ſo far from enabling any Prince to invade thereby the Property of any Subject, that it is the greateſt ſecurity to them: For by ſuch ſpeedy Transferring Eſtates, as may be done by a publick Regiſter, even Forfeitures to the Crown may be prevented, when every one, in ſome few hours, may paſs their Eſtates, Real, or Perſonal, into what ſecure hands they pleaſe.</p>
               <p>It is likewiſe obvious, how many frauds would be prevented by it, and how much more plentiful Mony would be, when none would be in danger of looſing either Purchaſe or Lent-mony, by Pre-Engagements; ſince fewer ſhifts could be uſed, to deceive any moderately circumſpect perſon. The Proceedings likewiſe in Law-Suits, would be leſs tedious and intricate, and yet many Hundreds of Clerks would find Imployment in Regiſtring, in every County and Corporate Town; and when mony Men could have ſuch ſuch clear Security, not haunted with the Spirit of Forgery, the middle ſort of Traders, the Husbandman, Farmers, and all ſort of Men, who had honeſt occaſions for ready Mony, might be furniſhed without ſo great ſcruple, which the doubtfulneſs of Security now occaſions.</p>
               <p>But theſe being matters to be Tranſacted in Parliament, need no further diſcuſſing here: Only I thought it neceſſary to hint theſe things, that all Ingenuous Men might ſee, how unreaſonable ſome Mens ſuſpicions are, and what ſiniſter Interpretations, Malice, and Envy, will make, of what is moſt apparently deſign'd for a quite different end.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:100804:26"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>In fine,</hi> Would we enjoy the free exerciſe of the <hi>Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion?</hi> We have the Kings Sacred Promiſe for it; and upon the taking off the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſt,</hi> we may have it firmly Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed: Would Diſſenters have Eaſe, they have it freely granted without Terms. Would we enjoy all the advantages of Wealth, Honour, Peace, Plenty, and the Benefits which a Gracious, Valiant, and Wiſe Prince may afford Us? We may to the height of our Wiſhes have them; yielding only, that our Fellow-Subjects in general, and thoſe of His Majeſties Religion in particular, may be all alike freed from any Force put upon their Conſcience for matters of their Religion, at preſent, and for time to come; while in all other Reſpects they approve themſelves Dutiful Subjects.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAge</hi> 4. <hi>line</hi> 23. <hi>for</hi> reaſonable <hi>read</hi> ſeaſonable. <hi>P.</hi> 5. <hi>l.</hi> 23. <hi>for</hi> gratefully, <hi>r.</hi> greatly. <hi>P.</hi> 7. <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>for</hi> hinder <hi>r.</hi> hindred. <hi>ibid. l.</hi> 39. <hi>dele</hi> of <hi>P.</hi> 9 <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>for</hi> ſuch (as Secluſion <hi>r.</hi> (ſuch as Secluſion. <hi>P.</hi> 11. <hi>l.</hi> 16. <hi>for</hi> Communion <hi>r.</hi> common<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>P.</hi> 16. <hi>l.</hi> 29. <hi>for</hi> cumlocution <hi>r.</hi> circumlocution.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
